<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Certaine points of christian religion]</title>
            <author>Saintbarb, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 209 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21556</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113423</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848657</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848657</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13766</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11295)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13766)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1692:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Certaine points of christian religion]</title>
                  <author>Saintbarb, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 55, 58-90 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For W. Young and R. Jackson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title and imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Richard Saintbarb.</note>
                  <note>The text is in question and answer format.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Certaine points of christian religion.</note>
                  <note>Imprint is from Maunsell (pt. 1 of STC 17669), who lists 2 works with this imprint: on C4r: "Rich. Saintbarb. his catechisme, wherein are chiefly handeled such things as are omitted in other catechismes." and on H6r: "Rich. Saintbarb, his exposition ont he creed, the Lords praier, Commandements and Sacraments, in questions and Aunsweers." The present text is probably the former.--STC.</note>
                  <note>List of errata on M8r, final page.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-M.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks leaves A1,2 (includes title page).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13766:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the right Honourable Sir <hi>Francis VValſingham</hi> Knight, Principall Secretarie to her Maieſtie, and <hi>of her Highneſſe moſt Honourable Priuie</hi> Counſell: And to the godlie and vertuous <hi>Ladie, the Ladie</hi> Vrſula <hi>his Wife:</hi> RICHARD SAINTBARB the vnworthie ſeruant and <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt, wiſheth great proſperitie in this</hi> life, with encreaſe of grace and peace from <hi>GOD the Father, and life euerlaſting</hi> through Ieſus Chriſt our life and Redeemer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ight I not <hi>(Right Honourable)</hi> ſeeme ouer bold, or might my preſumption therein be pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: I ſhould not only then hold my ſelfe freed from one of my chiefeſt cares, but alſo it woulde miniſter greate ioy vnto my diſtruſtfull and fearefull mind. For now I reſt doubtfull to make your Honours defenders of theſe my firſt fruites &amp; ſimple labours: but I cannot on the ſudden comfort my timorous and weake ſpirit with poſſeſſion of ſuch your fauours (and that it were vnmeete that good thinges ſhould be hindred &amp; buried for anie perticular reſpect,
<pb facs="tcp:13766:2"/>
I wil reſerue vnto my ſelfe the hope of your good and godlie likings: and ſo as one who as well by the report of Gods deere children, both of preachers and others, as in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure himſelfe hath beene made acquainted with your holie &amp; religious diſpoſitions not onely in ſauouring good things and the truth of the Goſpell which is the power of God to ſaluation. <hi>Rom. 1.16.</hi> but alſo in furthering by all good &amp; godly meanes the building vp of the beawtifull and precious houſe of God that the ſanctified ſpouſe of Chriſt <hi>Epheſ. 5.</hi> might bee edified and furthered in all ſound knowledge and holie faith. <hi>2. Pet. 1.5, 6, 7, 8.</hi> I wholly therefore depend vpon your fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable acceptance of the cauſe I handle, which I doubt not, but throughlie aſſure my ſelfe it ſhall doe great good in the Church of God: and bring ſinguler profite vnto Gods deare Saintes: and thus being reſolued, that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard thereof, your Honours will vouchſafe to beare with my raſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſſe and weakeneſſe, and take to your defence this godlie treatiſe of the grounds and principall queſtions of chriſtian Religion: my proceeding wherein I leaue to be cenſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by your wiſe and ſound
<pb facs="tcp:13766:2"/>
iudgments: little regarding the carping mate and curious reader either of proud papiſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Heriticke, diſſembling hipocrite or blind Atheiſt who neuer with godlie reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence regard the truth of Chriſt, neither the deuiding of the worde of God aright. And thus praying that GOD of his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies will bleſſe your Honours with all his good bleſſings, I humblie take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Kingswood in Wilt.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the 2. of September, 1589.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours moſt humblie to commaund in the Lord Jeſus,</hi> Richard Saintbarb <hi>Preacher of Gods word.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13766:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>¶ To the chriſtian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> grace and peace in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eere Chriſtians, if euer good <hi>Dauid</hi> had iuſt cauſe to crie out &amp; ſay, <hi>My eies guſh out with riuers of waters becauſe they keep not the law.</hi> Pſa. 119.136. If the ſame Prophets heart did tremble and ſhake for feare of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, when he ſaw the flowing wickedneſſe of his time, and the heauie hand of God for the ſame; for theſe are his words, <hi>Thou haſt tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den downe all them that depart from thy ſtatutes: for their deceit is vain. Thou haſt taken away all the wicked of the earth like droſſe; therefore I loue thy teſtimonies,
<pb facs="tcp:13766:3"/>
my fleſh trembleth for feare of thee, and I am afraid of thy iudgments,</hi> Pſal. 119.118, 119, 120. Jf euer <hi>Lot, Ieremie,</hi> and the godlie men that are recorded in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> had iust cauſe to mourne &amp; pine awaie with great griefe and zeale, in beholding the contempt and despi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Gods ſacred lawe, &amp; the most abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable life of the people in their daies. How much more may the godlie Miniſters, and all good people weepe and conſume themſelues away and ſend foorth euerie daie fountaines of teares, to behold, and continuallie to ſee this our age and time, (which ſhould be a most happie time for knowledge, faith, and holineſſe of life, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how long a ſeaſon God hath lent vnto vs his holie word, and powred his benefites vppon vs) which are yet a moſt crooked and ſtiff-nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked generation: for the hearts of the people are not onely become hard and ſtonie, but alſo their eares (as the Prophet Ieremie ſaith) are become vncircumciſed, that they cannot abide to heare Gods word: yea it is a reproach vnto them, and they haue no delight therein: <hi>Iere. 6.10.</hi> alſo how ſinne aboundeth J neede not to ſhew: for this our land lieth in ſinnes, and is froſen in the dregges thereof: <hi>Zephaniah, 1.12.</hi> Euen ſo
<pb facs="tcp:13766:4"/>
much that we iuſtifie <hi>Zodama</hi> and <hi>Gomora, Ezeki. 16.</hi> for iuſt and holie Cities: for ſuch are the ſinnes of <hi>England,</hi> and ſo vile, that it maie rather be accounted a polluted Land, and a ſeat of iniquitie: for (alack) how deepelie is ſhe ſunken in the ſinke of ſinne, and how abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nablie doth ſhee ſend foorth euerie day more &amp; more all kindes of Pride, Whoredomes, Inceſts, Murthers, Theftes, Couetouſnes, Oppreſſions, Vſuries, Curſings, Periuries, Blaeſphemies, and ſuch like: in ſo much that we may ſaie with the holie &amp; good Prophet <hi>Hoſea, Hear the word of the Lord ye childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael</hi> (yea rather ye children &amp; inhabitants of England) <hi>for the Lord hath a controuerſie with the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the lande becauſe there is no truth nor mercie, nor knowledge of God in the lande. By ſwearing and lying killing and ſtealing, and whoring, they breake out, and bloud toucheth bloud: Therefore ſhall the land mourne &amp; euerie one that dwelleth therein ſhall bee cut off with the beaſts of the field, and the foules of the Heauen, and alſo the fiſhes of the ſea ſhall be taken away: yet let none rebuke nor reprooue other, for thy people are as
<pb facs="tcp:13766:4"/>
they that rebuke the Prieſts.</hi> Hoſea 4.1, 2, 3, 4. and what is the fountaine and cauſe of theſe euils and rebellious tranſgreſſions: ſuerly infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie and ignorance of Gods word (as the good Apoſtle <hi>S. Paule</hi> affirmeth in theſe wordes). <hi>This I ſay therefore and teſtifie in the Lord that ye henceforth walk not as other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles walk in vanitie of their minde, hauing their cogitation darkned, and being ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from the life of God, through the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that is in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe of the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their heart, which beeing paſt fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, haue giuen themſelues vnto wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to worke all vncleanneſſe euen with greedineſſe.</hi> Eph. 4.17, 18, 19. <hi>I beſeech you therefore deare brethren,</hi> and good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>by the mercies of God, that ye giue vp your bodies a liuing ſacrifice, holy and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, which is your reſonable ſeruing of God; &amp; faſhion not your ſelues like vnto this world, but be yee changed by the renuing of your minde, that ye may proue what is the good will of God, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, and perfect.</hi> Rom. 12.1, 2. And this time of ignorance (as the ſame Apoſtle testifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) God regardeth not: but he admoniſheth al
<pb facs="tcp:13766:5"/>
men euerie where to repent. Act. 17.30. Againe, <hi>Awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ſtand vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead, and Chriſt ſhall giue thee light: wherefore be not vnwiſe, but vnderſtand what the will of the Lord is.</hi> Eph. 5.14, 17. <hi>That we being filled with the knowledge of his will in all wiſedome and ſpirituall vnderſtanding, may walke worthie of the Lord, and pleaſe him in all things, beeing fruitful in all good works.</hi> Col. 1.9, 10. And that this knowledge, faith, and fruitfulneſſe in all good workes may abound in vs, as the elect &amp; deer childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, let vs dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly read the book of god, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually meditate on the ſame for the Prophet ſaith. <hi>Bleſſed is the man, that doth not walke in the counſell of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, nor ſtand in the way of ſinners, nor ſit in the ſeate of the ſcorneful: but his delight is in the Lawe of the Lord, and in his Lawe doth he meditate day &amp; night: for he ſhall be like a tree planted by the riuers of waters that wil bring foorth her fruite in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: whoſe leafe ſhall not fade, ſo whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he ſhall do, ſhall proſper. Pſal. 1.1.2, 3.</hi> Now, for the common benefit, and better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Gods people and thy ſelfe: (christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb facs="tcp:13766:5"/>
reader) J haue cauſed this little and ſhort treatiſe of christian points of religion, to be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and publiſhed: and although, it bee but ſmall in volume, yet I doubt not, but if it be well read and printed in minde, it ſhall minister great good, to further thy knowledge, to confirm thy faith, and to increaſe true holines in thee. And this I dare promiſe thee, that there are ſome things handled in this Catechiſme, both in matter and manner, which other Catechiſmes dooth not as once meddle and intreate of, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, which are intreated of ſome in their bookes, haue J drawne in a briefe method, for the benifit of the reader. And whereas many things are yet in doubt among the multitude and great controuerſies doo riſe by them, I haue breefely, yet ſoundly opened the trueth of them: finally there is not that point, which I haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of, but I haue first defined the ſame, and haue ſet downe the definitions, of all the hardeſt words, which are commonly vſed by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the word, and in the large and great volumes of the learned; that the ſimple, who is altogether ignorant of the true ſenſe of them, may vnderſtand, not onely the Preacher and bookes, which they both heare and read, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:13766:6"/>
the verie words as iustification, ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, grace, redemption, law and ſuch like. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing my purpoſe is onely to doo good vnto Gods Church, and my paine great herein, yet godly, I hope all faithfull people will accept the ſame and both praiſe God for this litle worke, and pray vnto God for mee, to increaſe his good gifts and graces in my ſoule vnto my liues end. Amen. Thus I take my leaue from my houſe at <hi>Kingſwood</hi> the ſecond of <hi>September.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord,</hi> Richard Saintbarb, <hi>Preacher of Gods word.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13766:6"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13766:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13766:7"/>
            <head>Certaine points of Christian Religion.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Nto what faith wert thou baptiſed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Into the faith of the holie Trinitie. <hi>Matth. 28.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What dooſt thou meane when thou ſaieſt, thou art baptiſed into the faith of the holie Trinitie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is to enter and conſecrate the baptiſed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the faith and religion of one God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that they might beleeue the Father, the Sonne, and the Holie ghoſt, to bee one God; to whom alone, they muſt giue their faith and confidence. <hi>Pſal. 37.5. Iere. 17.5, 6, 7, 8. Iohn. 14.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that they beleeue, that the ſonne and the holie ghoſt, are nothing els but the verie eſſence of God. <hi>1. Iohn 5.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that they confeſſe God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who hath adopted them, God the ſonne by whome they are redeemed, and God the
<pb facs="tcp:13766:8"/>
holie Ghoſt, by whome they are ſanctified &amp; confirmed. <hi>Gala. 4.4, 5, 6. 1. Corinthians 6.10, 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where ſhall wee finde the ſumme of this faith of the holie Trinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, generallie at large in the holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which is called the Booke of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, particularlie and briefely in the Articles of the Faith, called the Apoſtles Creede.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why is it ſo called?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For two apt cauſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe it is a briefe collection of the Articles of the Faith, which haue been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in Chriſts Church.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe it was taken out of the pure doctrine of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why muſt euerie chriſtian ſay <hi>I beleeue,</hi> &amp; not <hi>We beleeue;</hi> as well as they generally do ſay <hi>Our Father which art, &amp;c.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:13766:8"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe euerie Chriſtian muſt be ſaued by his owne faith, and not by an others.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wheras we ſay, <hi>Our Father,</hi> we muſt note, that it is a prayer: and the other the beleefe of euerie Chriſtian, and therefore a plaine and great difference, <hi>Haba. 2.4. Ga. 3.11. Heb. 10.38, 39.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why muſt we beleeue, that <hi>there is a Church,</hi> &amp; not <hi>in the Church,</hi> as <hi>in God the Father, &amp;c?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were great idolatrie, to put our truſt in meere man; for Faith onely belongeth to the holy Trinitie: and although Ieſus Chriſt who is ſaluation it ſelfe, is no where to be found but in the Church; yet Saluation is not of the Church, and therefore <hi>Ieremie</hi> accurſeth them that put anie confidence in the fleſh of ſinfull man. <hi>Iohn 17.1, 2, 3. Matth. 28.19. Ierem. 17.5, 6. Eſay, 30.1, 2, 3, 4.</hi> and <hi>31.1, 2, 3, 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Into how manie points ſhall we diuide this confeſsion of our faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:9"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Into <hi>3.</hi> The firſt concerning God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the firſt Article.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, concerning God the Sonne in the ſixe next Articles.</p>
            <p>The third, concerning God the holy Ghoſt in the fiue laſt Articles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How manie things learn you in the firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle? <hi>I beleeue in God the father Almightie, &amp;c.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, what God is.</p>
            <p>Secondly, how he created all things.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, how he preſerueth all his workes.</p>
            <p>Fourthlie, how he ruleth and gouerneth all things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God is a ſpirite, infinite, euerlaſting, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaungeable, incorruptible, immortall, moſt ſimple in nature; in power moſt mightie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible both in greatneſſe and Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, (by whom all things were made in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of nothing) alſo diſtinguiſhed into thrée perſons: the Father, the Sonne, and the holie
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13766:9"/>
Ghoſt. <hi>Iohn 4.24. Eſay 66.1, 2. Eſay 40.28. Mal. 3.6. Iam. 1.17. Rom. 1.23. 2. Tim. 1.17. Gen. 17.1. Rom. 11.33, 34, 35, 36. Ier. 10.10, 11, 12, 13. Matth. 28.19. Reuel. 15.3, 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is God the Father?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee is the beginning and Authour of euerie thing both in heauen and in earth. Who, when it ſéemed good vnto his diuine Nature, created all things of nothing, in heauen and in earth, both ſpirituall and corporall, and ordered them by his eternall Sonne: the which are now go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned and mainteined, by the infinite and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiall power of the Holie Ghoſt, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from them both from all eternitie. <hi>Gen. 1.1, 2, &amp;c. Gene. 2.1. Prouerb. 8.14, to the end. Pſalme 114.30. Gene. 1.2. Iohn 15.26. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. 8.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the Sonne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sonne of God, is Ieſus Chriſt, who was begotten of his Father before all worlds; and of his Father (without a mother) by whom all things were created: who (being appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:13766:10"/>
of his Father from euerlaſting to redeeme his elect people) was (when the fulneſſe of time was come) borne of a Virgin, and became man of his mother (without a father,) by whom we are ſaued <hi>Pſalm. 2.7. Hebr. 1.5. Iohn 1.14, 18. Col. 1.16, 17. Reuela. 13.8. 1. Peter 1.19, 20. Galath. 4.4, 5. Luke 1.26, 27, 30, 31. Luke 2.6, 7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the Holie Ghoſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Holie Ghoſt is the eſſentiall power and vertue, both of the Father and the Sonne, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and conſubſtantiall with them: in whome, he reſteth and abideth; and from whom, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth: By him, are we grafted into the bodie of Chriſt, and ſanctified, and ſealed vp to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Iohn 15.26. Luk. 11.20. Gen. 1.2. 1. cor. 12.13, 14. Tit. 3.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In that thou ſaieſt, there is God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the Holie Ghoſt: what dooſt thou els, but make three Gods?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No, not ſo: for God is one in eſſence, and ſimple in nature, although thrée Perſons diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13766:10"/>
out of the ſame Beeing of Beeings. <hi>Deuter. 6.4. 1. Corinth. 8.6. Epheſians 4.5, 6. 1. Iohn. 5.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How proue you this diſtinction of the three Perſons in the one Godhead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This maye bee prooued moſt plainelie and firmlie by theſe places of Scripture, <hi>Matthew 3.16, 17.</hi> and <hi>28.19. 1. Iohn 5.7. Romanes, 8.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Are they three ſeuerall ſubſtances, in that they are three diſtinct perſons?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: for I haue alreadie ſaid, that they are but one, imcomprehenſible, infinite, inuiſible, and vndeuidable ſubſtance, and yet three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How are they three Perſons?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In reſpect of their properties, and not in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding their nature, but in diſtinguiſhing their properties.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:11"/>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What are their properties?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We attribute to God the father, our Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: to God the ſonne, our redemption: and to God the holie Ghoſt, our ſanctification: to the father, the thing done; to the Sonne, the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome whereby it is done; to the Holie Ghoſt, the effects of the thing done. <hi>Geneſ. 2.7. Titus 2.14. 1. Peter 1.2. Actes 14.15. Prouerbes 8.22, to 32.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What things are proper to the Father alone, that agree neither to the Sonne, nor to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This: the begetting of the Sonne; for which cauſe, he is called the Father, and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Trinitie. <hi>Iohn 3.16. 1. Cor. 8.6. Iohn 16.28. and 15.26.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is giuen to the Sonne, that is not likewiſe giuen to the Father, nor to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be begotten; for which cauſe he is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13766:11"/>
the Sonne, and ſeconde perſon in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head; as alſo, that he is the Fathers word. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes 2.5. 1. Iohn 4.9. Matthew 28.19. Iohn 1.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is proper to the Holie Ghoſt, that is not likewiſe giuen to the Father, nor to the Sonne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be proceeding from the Father and the Sonne, and to be the third perſon in Trinitie. <hi>Rom. 8.9. Matth. 28.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then Ieſus Chriſt was not created, in that he was the Sonne of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No verelie: but begotten from euerlaſting, and without beginning: Alſo in that he is God he is the Creator, and not a creature: for, <hi>by him all things were made. <hi>Reuelat. 1.8. Mich. 5.2. Iohn 17.5. Iohn 1.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. Coloſſ. 1.16, 17.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Was Ieſus Chriſt created, in that hee is man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:12"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea: hee was created of God without the helpe of man, onely by the worke and operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the holie Ghoſt, in the wombe of the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Marie. <hi>Matth. 1.20. Luke 1.35. Galath. 4.4.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In that thou giueſt Ieſus Chriſt two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, what dooeſt thou elſe but make two Chriſts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: Although we ſay, that in Chriſt there be two natures, as diuine and humane; yet we make not two Chriſtes, nor two perſons, but one perſon, and one Chriſt; conſiſting of two natures. <hi>Matth. 1.21, 23. Rom. 1.3, 4. Luke. 1.43. Rom. 9.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is Ieſus Chriſt, as he is man, the Sonne of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No verelie: not in that hee is man, but in that he is God: and he is the Sonne of man, and ſo called, in that he is man. <hi>Luke. 1.35. Matth. 26.64.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:13766:12"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet there is but one Sonne of God, as there is but one Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is moſt true: There is not one eternall and naturall: and another created and adopted; but that onelie eternal Sonne of God, who ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaineth &amp; vpholdeth, the nature vnited to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Yet muſt we note, that we call the perſon of Chriſt; <hi>the Sonne of God manifeſted in the fleſh. <hi>2. Tim. 3.16.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then, is it thy meaning, that the humane nature of Chriſt is a perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: for Chriſtes humane Nature, was neuer extant or had beeing, but in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head: wherefore the humane nature in Chriſt, is not a Perſon; but the humanitie ſubſiſteth, and hath his being in the perſon of the Word, and therefore Chriſt is not either in imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or in déede, a double Perſon; but one Perſon conſiſting of two Natures. <hi>Iohn. 1.14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:13"/>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the perſonall vnion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the taking of mans nature, which is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteined and vpholden of the diuine nature (that is to ſay) ſuch a taking or vniting, that there procéedeth or commeth out of that vniting, but one ſubſiſtence one beeing onely; in which ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence that diuine nature (that is to ſaye) the perſon of the Word, beareth ſwaie and ruleth. <hi>1. Ioh. 1.1, 2, 3. Rom. 1.3, 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea: but he is alſo called the Sonne of God in that he is God and man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true: but not naturallie in reſpect of his manhood, but by reaſon of the Perſonall v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, with his diuine nature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proceede vnto the Holie Ghoſt: and tell me, is he created, or begotten?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither: but proceeding from the Father and the Sonne, of the ſame ſubſtance and bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them: equall with the Father and the Sonne in glorie and maieſtie, and from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternities,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13766:13"/>
as in the definition it was ſhewed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea: but it ſhoulde ſeeme, that the Father ſhould be greater than the Sonne: &amp; the Sonne greater than the holie Ghoſt, becauſe the one is placed before the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not ſo: For although the Father is put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sonne in order, and the Father and the Sonne before the Holie Ghoſt; yet it is not becauſe the one is greater than the other, or more excellent than the other: but becauſe the Sonne was begotten of the Father, and the Holie Ghoſt proceeding from the Father and the Sonne. Otherwiſe we ſhall read firſt, how the Sonne is put before the Father, <hi>2. Cor. 13.</hi> And alſo how the Spirit is put in the firſt place <hi>1. Corinth. 12.</hi> Whereby we may note, that the order of names doth not make difference of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities.</p>
            <p>Secondlie they be one in eſſence and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. <hi>1. Iohn. 5.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that which is giuen to the one is giuen to the other in giftes and working, <hi>Iohn 5.21.26.27. 1. Cor. 12.4. to 12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:14"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then there is but one nature of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is moſt true: and that vncorrupt, infinite, vnbegotten, neither diuided by place, nor inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in anie place, nor ſecluded out of anie place, nor defiled by perſon or place, neither ſubiect to change. <hi>Rom. 1.23. 1. Tim. 6.16. Pſal. 139.7.</hi> to <hi>14. Eſay 46.10. Iam. 1.17. Deut. 32.4. Pſal. 5.4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now ſhew me what is a perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Perſon is a ſubſiſtance in the Eſſence of God: which being referred vnto the reſt, is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by a certaine incommunicable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie, or which is not common to the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then a ſubſiſtance is another thing than an eſſence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true: for if the Word were ſimply God, and had nothing proper ſeuerally to it ſelf: then had the holie Euangeliſt <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaid ill, when he ſaid: <hi>The Word</hi> (which he afterwards calleth God) <hi>was with God. <hi>Iohn. 1.2, 3.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:13766:14"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the vſe of this deepe myſterie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are taught hereby: Firſt, how we ought in all diuine wiſedome and godlie humilitie, to reuerence this deepe and holie myſterie of the Trinitie (the Father, the Sonne, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt) and yet but one God in being and glorie, contrarie to the opinion of <hi>Sabellius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, how Chriſt was both God &amp; man.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God from euerlaſting, and begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of his Father before all times, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the hereſie of <hi>Arius, <hi>Iohn. 1.1, 2. Micah. 5.2. Reuel. 22.13.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Man when the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nes of time was come, by taking fleſh of the Virgine <hi>Marie:</hi> not bringing the ſame fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen from the Father, &amp; ſo afterward ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp of the Father, &amp; became al one with him, as <hi>Marcellus</hi> the heretike affirmed, alſo renewed by the Anabaptiſts. <hi>Rom. 1.3, 4. Gal. 4.4. Heb. 2.16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that the holy Ghoſt is God with the Father and the Sonne, of the ſame bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and glorie from all eternities, <hi>Gene. 1.2. Eſay 48.16. Math. 12.32. 2. Cor. 5.19.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb facs="tcp:13766:15"/>
to the hereſie of the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> who denied the Diuinitie of the holie Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it teacheth vs to praie vnto Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, and ſearch after true wiſedom and vnderſtanding; that we may both be led into the true myſterie, and auoide al hereſies herein. <hi>Matth. 7.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nowe let vs proceede vnto the ſeconde point of the diuiſion: namely of the creation of the world, tell me what order wilt thou ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue herein?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, firſt of creation generallie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of creation particularlie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let vs then come to the firſt, was the world without beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: for it was created, although the philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers did dream the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie. <hi>Gen. 1.1, 2.</hi> &amp; <hi>2.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who created the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Almightie God, by his wiſedome and power. <hi>Gen. 2.1, 2, 3, 4. Iohn. 1.1, 2, 3, 4. Prouerb. 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:13766:15"/>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is creation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Creation is that action of God, whereby hée created and made of nothing, all thinges, both Heauen and earth, and whatſoeuer is conteined in them, when that there was none of them. <hi>Gen. 1.12. Pſal. 33.6. Iere. 10. Acts. 14.15. Iohn. 1.1, 2, 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Were they created ſuch as they bee now? Or in what eſtate where they created at the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching their nature it is all one, but the qualities and conditions of them, are meruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſlie altered and changed: for whereas now we ſee them ſubiect to vanitie, they were not ſo then, but created verie good and perfect, for that the worke did ſufficientlie preach and ſet foorth the glorie and cunning of the worke man, as it is plainelie ſet downe in the booke of <hi>Geneſis</hi> thus: <hi>The Lord ſawe all that he had made, and it was very good. <hi>Gen. 1.31.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How came this ruine and confuſion to the creatures, which were created perfect by God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:16"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Onely by the Apoſtacie and fall of man, who was appointed of God to be Lorde and ruler o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the whole world, and all the creatures there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>Gene. 3.17.18. Rom. 8.20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Were all creatures that are now mouing and growing vpon the earth, then made?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: for God in his iuſtice, to puniſh the fall and apoſtacie of <hi>Adam</hi> and mankinde (yet iuſt &amp; good in God, did cauſe the earth to bring forth (thorough corruption) many noiſome and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt creatures (ſince the ſixe dayes) which were not created at the firſt: for it is ſaide, that all the works of God were very good. <hi>Gen. 1.31.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How prooueſt thou that ſuch noiſome crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, were created after the fall of man, and for his puniſhment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the words of GOD, which the holy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of God <hi>Moſes</hi> rehearſeth in <hi>Gene. 3.17, 18. <hi>Curſed be the earth for thy ſake, thornes alſo, and thistles ſhall it cauſe to growe vnto thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o that whatſoeuer corrupt things doo growe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13766:16"/>
and proceede from corruption, they are not the natural fruits of the earth (as reckned in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of nature) but corruptions, and of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which haue their originall of ſinne: as lice, fleas, flies, frogges, toades, catterpillers, graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers, ſpiders, briers, thiſtles, and ſuch like noyſome and hurtfull creatures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shall the heauens and the earth be conſumed, (becauſe the Elements, the Ayre, and the earth, are corrupted by corruption) in their ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, at the day of Iudgement, and ſo a new hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and a new earth created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: but they ſhall bee renewed and purged from their corruptions, which the ſinne of man brought into the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea, but it is written by S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> that GOD will make a new Heauen and a new earth, and that the firſt Heauen and earth ſhall fleete a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from before him, and their place ſhall bee no more founde. <hi>Reuel. 20.11, 12.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> meaning is not, that there ſhoulde bee a newe Heauen and a newe earth,
<pb facs="tcp:13766:17"/>
in reſpect of new, and other ſubſtances then they were before; but when Chriſt ſhall appeare, hée ſhall chaſe away, and purge all the corruptions of the Elements and the earth, with his purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and pure fire. <hi>Heb. 1.11. 2. Pet. 3.12, 13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What other proofe haue you for this thing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This: the holie Ghoſt will not bee againſt himſelfe; for he ſheweth by his Apoſtle, that the heauens and the earth ſhall be reſtored, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from all corruption; but yet in their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to remaine. <hi>Roma. 8.19,</hi> to <hi>23. Actes 3.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rehearſe the words of the firſt place?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the feruent deſire of the creature</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paule,) <hi>waiteth when the ſonnes of God ſhall be reuealed, becauſe the creature is ſubiect to vanitie, not of it owne will, but of him which hath ſubdued it vnder hope, becauſe the creatures alſo ſhall be deliuered from the bondage of corruption, into the glorious libertie of the ſonnes of God: for wee knowe that euerie creature groneth with vs alſo, and traueleth in paine together vnto this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13766:17"/>
and not onlie the creature, but we alſo.</hi> Rom. 8.19, 20, 21, 22, 23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What gathereſt thou out of theſe words?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt by this word <hi>Creature,</hi> is ment all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that liue, mooue, and growe, vpon, in or vnder the earth, both ſenceles and ſenſible, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and without life; and not onely Angels, men, or diuels; and therefore the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>euerie Creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the Apoſtle ſaieth, <hi>that they waight for the glorious libertie of the ſonnes of God that they alſo might be</hi> not deſtroyed, but <hi>deliuered from the bondage of coruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, hee ſaieth, that <hi>they are ſubdued vnder hope,</hi> namelie of reſtoration to that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent eſtate that they had by creation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proceede to your ſecond place of proofe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whome the Heauens must conteine vntill the time that all things bee restored, which God had ſpoke by the mouth of all the holy Prophets ſince the world began. <hi>Actes 3.21.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:18"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What gather you by theſe words?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That al things ſhal be reſtored to an excellent perfection, and therfore S. <hi>Peter</hi> calleth the day of Iudgement, the day of reſtoring of al things: which could not be attributed vnto that day, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that there ſhould be a reſtoration of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To what end or what vſes, ſhall they ſerue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the day of Iudgement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is a wicked curioſitie, to ſearch after thoſe things which God hath not reuealed vnto vs: let vs therefore ſay with <hi>Moſes, <hi>The ſecret things belong vnto the Lord our GOD: and the things reuealed vnto vs and our children for euer, that we may doo all the words of this Lawe.</hi> Deu. 29.29.</hi> and ſo auoide likewiſe, ſuch vaine que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions as theſe: whether they ſhall be perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all or not perpetuall, for vſes or not for vſes; for they breed but ſtrife and meere babling. <hi>1. Tim. 1.4, 5, 6, 7. Titus 3.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the vſe of this point?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:13766:18"/>Firſt, how all things were created of God moſt perfect and good at the firſt; and he therfore holy and iuſt in his works. <hi>Pſalm. 145.10, 11. Deut. 32.4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, how our ſinne was the ruine and confuſion of the perfection and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the creatures in their firſt creation: ſo that hereby we may ſee how horrible and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie a thing ſinne is: and therefore ſo much the more to hate the ſame. <hi>Gene. 4.11, 12. Ephe. 2.2, 3. Col. 3.1, 2, 3, 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly the iuſtice of GOD in puniſhing ſin; and therfore we ought to kil and flie from the ſame, as the only enemy of our health and ſaluation. <hi>Pſal. 5.4, 5, 6. Co. 3.5, 6. Ro. 6.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, how all things in Chriſt, ſhall bee reſtored to health and the former excellencie; but man to a greater excellencie, and more perfect happines than at the firſt. <hi>Rom. 8.14.</hi> to <hi>26.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As wee haue hetherto intreated generallie of the creation of the world, with all things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: ſo now more particularlie let vs come to the making and creating of man: the which is the ſecond point, and tell me what order thou wilt keepe herein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:19"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, who made man.</p>
            <p>Secondly, whereof he conſiſteth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, of his excellencie in his firſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, of his fall.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, how wee come to the knowledge thereof and our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, of the vſes of the lawe and good workes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who made man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What things may we conſider in God, in the creation of man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, his wiſdome. <hi>Pſalm. 104.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, his power.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, his goodnes. <hi>Pſalm. 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let vs come to the ſecond thing: What is man, and whereof dooth he conſiſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man is an excellent and reaſonable creature,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13766:19"/>
created after the image of God his creator con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of two partes. <hi>Gene. 1.26, 27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, a ſoule. <hi>Gene. 2.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Second, a bodie. <hi>Eccle. 12.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the bodie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A wonderfull Creature of the workeman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, framed out of the duſt of the earth, and of a notable proportion in euerie parte; made vpright, to looke vpward alwaies to God his maker. <hi>Gene. 3.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Although the bodie bee of the duſt of the earth, is it not yet more excellent than all other creatures that were made of the earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes verelie: and that firſt, in reſpect of the time of his creation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of the forme of his creation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, of the end of his creation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, of the perſon of the Sonne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1 How in the time of his creation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Lorde made man, hee firſt tooke
<pb facs="tcp:13766:20"/>
counſell of his wiſdome and power, and delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated on the matter: but when he made all other creatures (before hee made man) hee ſaide: <hi>let it be done,</hi> and it was done preſentlie, not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſuch deliberation on their Creation, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his wiſdome, power and glorie may bée ſeene in them. <hi>Gen. 1.26. Roma. 1.20, 21.</hi> and <hi>11.36.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2 How informe of his creation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God made all other creatures to go groue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on the earth, and to looke downeward, but he made man a ſtreight bodie to go vpright; and alway to looke vp into Heauen, and ſo to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his Creator: alſo, he hath planted a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Maieſtie in the face of man, to the terror of all other creatures. <hi>Gene. 1.28, 29.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3 How in the end of his creation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in glorifying GOD in holy words, and alſo in good workes. <hi>Epheſians 4.29, 30. Matth. 5.16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in reſpect of the redemption of the bodie thorough Chriſt, <hi>to be the childe of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13766:20"/>
God and heire of eternall life and ſaluation. <hi>Ro. 18.7.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, to bee <hi>the temple of the holy Ghoſt. <hi>1. Cor. 3.16.</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>6.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4. How in the perſon of the Sonne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that Chriſt the ſonne of God, hath onely communicated with man, in taking to himſelfe mans nature. <hi>Heb. 2.16. Rom. 1.3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What hath man to conſider in that his body is made of the earth and aduanced to ſuch glorie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, it beateth downe all pride. <hi>Iere. 22.29.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, his brittlenes is ſhewed therin. <hi>Iſay 40.6, 7, 8. Iob. 14.1, 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, it teacheth man to conſider his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie in Chriſt, and not to defile (in ſinne and vncleanenes of life) his bodie. <hi>1. Cor. 6.15,</hi> to the end, <hi>2. Cor. 6.14,</hi> to the end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the ſoule?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is an immortall and ſpirituall ſubſtance created of GOD, and infuſed into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,
<pb facs="tcp:13766:21"/>
which quickneth and giueth life thereunto: and of it ſelfe neuer dieth. <hi>Eccle. 12.7. Iob. 10.12. Matth. 10.28. Reue. 6.9, 10, 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What are the powers of the ſoule?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Principallie two?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, reaſon. <hi>Eſay 29.9. 1. Theſ. 5.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, will. <hi>Heb. 4.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Are they perfect in vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: but moſt imperfect. <hi>Gen. 6.5. Ier. 17.9. Matth. 15.19, 20. Rom. 8.7. 1. Cor. 2.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Were they ſo created in vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: but we got corruption by the fall of our firſt parents, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue. Gen. 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. 2. Cor. 11.3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſaieſt that the ſoule is a ſpirituall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: but there are ſome that doo affirme, it is but a motion, other ſome, to bee a vaniſhing breath?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:13766:21"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Scripture teacheth the contrarie, for</p>
            <p>Firſt, God is called <hi>the father of the ſpirits. <hi>Heb. 12.9.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Chriſt is called <hi>the paſtour of ſoules. <hi>1. Pet. 2.25.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if theſe ſentences ſhal be applied to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and a vaniſhing breath; thereby to make God a Father, and Chriſt a Paſtour of a thing of naught, it were moſt wicked and abſurde.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the ſoule is ſubiect to torments, and capable of ioy in this world, and in the life to come: which things cannot be applied, to motions and a vaniſhing breath. <hi>Luk. 16.24, 25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, it ſhoulde than followe, ſo many motions, and breathes (ſeeing they haue no being) ſo many ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the definition it is ſaid that it neuer dieth, but alwaies liueth and is immortall, but there are ſome that affirme, that it ſleepeth, other ſome that it dieth with the bodie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That it neither ſleepeth, nor yet dieth, but that it alwaies liueth and is immortall: and that
<pb facs="tcp:13766:22"/>
either it goeth vnto bliſſe or miſerie preſentlie after the ſeperation of the body; proued. <hi>Eccl. 12.7. Mat. 22.31. Luk. 16.24, 25. Reu. 6.9, 10, 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo it is ſaid in the definition, that it is crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God, and by him infuſed into the bodie, but there are ſome that hold, that the ſoule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth the ſoule?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, theſe teſtimonies of holy Scripture do ſufficiently prooue, that they are created of God, and powred by him into the bodie. <hi>Eccleſ. 22.7. Pſal. 33.15. Iob. 10.9, 10, 11, 12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it is againſt the nature of a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to be deuided and parted.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſoule hath ſeed &amp; gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, is a hard and ſtrange kind of diuinity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Apoſtle <hi>Paule,</hi> diuideth man into three parts, the ſpirit, the ſoule, and the bodie: ſo that hee ſeemeth to make the ſpirit one thing, and the ſoule another: how is it then, that you di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide man into two partes, the ſoule, and bodie? <hi>1. Theſ. 5.23.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle diuideth the ſoule into two
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13766:22"/>
partes, the firſt is reaſon and vnderſtanding, which he calleth the ſpirit; the ſecond is wil and affection, which he calleth the ſoule: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſpirit is not a ſeuerall ſubſtance, but the ſoule &amp; ſpirit are one, euen as the bodie and fleſh are one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now let vs come vnto the third point, as thou haſt ſhewed that God made man; ſo tel me did he make him perfect and free from all ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea: for it is ſaid, that God did make him in the image of God. <hi>Gene. 1.27. Eccleſ. 7.31.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In that <hi>Moſes</hi> bringeth foorth God ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after this manner, <hi>let vs make man in our image,</hi> did he ſpeak vnto Angels, or the earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No verely, neither to the one nor to the other, for</p>
            <p>Firſt, what fit counſeller is the earth which is a dead Element.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to aſcribe ſuch a notable worke as the creation of man, or the leaſt part ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vnto Angels, is blaſphemie againſt God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is not ſaid that man was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted after the image of earth or Angels, but in the image of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:23"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the true meaning of the words?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God in that place, ſpeaketh vnto his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and power, ſhewing thereby what a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble creature man ſhould bee: alſo it is a notable place to proue the Trinitie of the perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doth <hi>Moſes</hi> make any difference betweene Image and likenes in that hee rehearſeth them both?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No verely, for by it <hi>Moſes</hi> repeateth one thing with many words, to make the ſame more plaine, and driue the ſame more deeply into our hearts. Alſo in the <hi>27.</hi> verſe he nameth only the word <hi>Image,</hi> finally in the fift chapter, the word <hi>ſimilitude</hi> he onely vſeth, and maketh no menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the word <hi>Image.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Was that the image of God, in reſpect of mans fourme or ſubſtance either in ſoule or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: for God hath no ſuch forme nor ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for he is neither fleſh, blood nor bone, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13766:23"/>
although a ſpiritual eſſence, yet infinite, vncrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and incomprehenſible. <hi>1. Reg. 8.27. Iob. 11.7, 8.</hi> and <hi>26.6.</hi> to the ende. <hi>Eſay. 40.12, 13. Rom. 11.33.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea: but the Scriptures doo attribute, head, eyes, eares, mouth, armes, and ſuch like thinges vnto God? <hi>Pſalme. 34.15, 16. Luke 1.51.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true, but theſe things are ſpoken for our weaknes, not that God hath ſuch things as are attributed vnto him: but by theſe things God dooth teach vs, and inſtruct vs further, in his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and vnſearchable myſteries; and becauſe we are too earthlie minded, therefore hee by theſe things doth lift vs vp to more excellent things; otherwiſe God is a ſpirite, inuiſible, infinit, and incomprehenſible.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo the Scriptures doo ſay, that <hi>he breathed into him the breath of life, and ſo made of him a liuing ſoule.</hi> This <hi>breath</hi> was of the ſubſtance of God: ſo the <hi>ſoule</hi> is a part of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his image.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is blaſphemie ſo to affirme, for the ſoule
<pb facs="tcp:13766:24"/>
was created of God, as the words maketh ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt: if it had been part of the Creator, then it could not haue been created; and what is this, but to make God ſubiect to errors, ſinne, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, afflictions and terrors, yea hell it ſelfe and the diuell: for the ſoule of man hath been ſubiect to theſe things, euer ſince the fall of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> &amp; <hi>Eua. Gen. 6.5. Ier. 17.9. 1. Sam. 15.29. Eph. 2.2, 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is it ſaid, that <hi>man was created in the image of God,</hi> becauſe Chriſt ſhould come who is the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: for <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaketh of the preſent time, when God made man. Again, what is this but to ſay, that man is an image of his image: and alſo that Chriſt ſhould be an image of himſelfe, and of the holie ſpirite, which thing is abſurd, &amp; a lying doctrine of diuels. <hi>Gen. 1.26, 27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How vnderſtand you theſe words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in <hi>Coloſſ. 1.15. Who is the image of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible God, the firſt borne of euerie creature.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:13766:24"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe words doo nothing belong to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the former abſurdities: but the Apoſtle telleth vs, that God ſheweth himſelfe to be ſéene in his ſonne Chriſt (not in that he had fleſh, head armes, eies, &amp;c.) but in his mercie, wiſedome, goodnes and righteouſnes: for otherwiſe, God in his naked Maieſtie, is inuiſible &amp; incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible, and by theſe words is proued againſt <hi>Arms,</hi> the coeſſence and conſubſtantialitie of the Sonne with the Father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are ſome that holde, that the image of God, was in man in reſpect of rule ouer the creatures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their iudgement is not right: for although the image of God did ſhine in ſome part; yet this is not <hi>Moſes</hi> meaning, when he ſaith, that man was created in the image of God; if it were, <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould be created vnto one image, and we reſtored into another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are others that doo affirme, that the image of God is in the ſoule, in reſpect of the
<pb facs="tcp:13766:25"/>
immortalitie: but as for true righteouſnes, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, &amp; wiſedome, &amp;c. they are but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of God, and not his image, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore man is not ſaid to be the image of GOD herein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They herein are greatly deceiued, for</p>
            <p>Firſt, if it be onely the immortalitie of the ſoule, then <hi>Adam</hi> hath loſt the ſame: for he by his Apoſtacie, loſt the image of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if it be the onely image of God wherein <hi>Adam</hi> was created, then is it not the ſame image wherein all true Chriſtians are nowe created; (as the Apoſtle ſheweth) which is, <hi>true righteouſneſſe and holineſſe:</hi> a thing too too abſurd. <hi>Eph. 4.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, by this it ſhould folow, that God hath <hi>2.</hi> images, which wer great blaſphemy.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, herein the lie is giuen to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ghoſt: for he plainly affirmeth by his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Word, that <hi>Adam</hi> was created into the ſame image, which we are now reſtored into by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But dooth not immortalitie repreſent the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God in ſome meaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13766:25"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes trulie in ſome part; but as I haue ſaid before, it is not <hi>Moſes</hi> meaning to call Man the image of God, onelie in that reſpect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But true righteouſneſſe, and holineſſe, &amp;c. are the properties of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I grant the ſame: yet it is the image of God wherein man was created, and the faithful now reſtored into through Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is this image of God wherin they were created?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the naturall conformitie of the ſoule, &amp; all the functions of it to the law of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by fréely and voluntarily it inclineth vnto true &amp; perfect holines &amp; righteouſnes. <hi>Eph. 4.24. Col. 3.10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where was this image placed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſoule, as the eſpeciall ſeate to rule all the powers thereof, to perfect and faithfull obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. <hi>Eph. 4.23. Rom. 12.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:26"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore was man created thus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſerue God his Creator in true righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; holines. <hi>Ge. 2.16, 17. Lu. 1.75. Eph. 4.24</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why ſaiſt thou, true righteouſnes &amp; holines?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe the ſame muſt be in ſinceritie, <hi>Ioh. 4.24. Eſay 29.13. Matth, 15.7, 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly according to the truth of Gods Word: otherwiſe it is but counterfet &amp; falſe. <hi>Deut. 4.2. Matth. 15.9. Ioh. 4.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is righteouſneſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a perfect rule of equitie, which teacheth vs to giue vnto euerie man his due, in worde, deede, and thought. <hi>Leuitie. 19.11, 15, 35, 36. 1. Theſſ, 4.6. Math. 7.12. Rom. 13.7, 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is holineſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a reuerent and holie obedience, in the worſhip of God, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioyned with a ſincere loue of God; which proceedeth from an effectuall faith,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13766:26"/>
in the knowledge of God, his word, &amp; workes. <hi>1. Sa. 15.22, 23. De. 6.5. Ro. 14.23. 2. Co. 4.13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let vs come vnto the 4. point, tell me, how fel we from this excellent image of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We fell through the deceit of Satan, &amp; the willing conſent of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eua,</hi> from the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God vnto the image of Satan, which is ſinne, fooliſhneſſe, &amp; all kind of blaſphemies. <hi>Gen. 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. 1. Ioh. 3.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What were the meanes, which Satan vſed to bereaue vs of this image of God, and our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe at the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two: externall, and internall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What are the externall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Three: <list>
                  <item>Firſt, the ſerpent, <hi>Gen. 3.1.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, the forbidden fruit. <hi>Ge. 3.2,</hi> to <hi>6.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thirdly, the woman. <hi>Gen. 3.6, 7.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What are the internall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:27"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Three. Firſt, infidelitie. <hi>Gen. 3.3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, ambition. <hi>Gen. 3.5, 6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſtubborne vnthankfulneſſe, <hi>Rom. 5.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What hath this fall brought vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It hath wrapped vs wholly in ſinne, &amp; made vs the children of wrath by nature. <hi>Geneſ. 6.5. Pſal. 51.6. Iob. 14.4. Matth. 15.19. Eph. 2.2, 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is originall ſinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the heritable corruption of our nature, which once was perfect in the innocencie of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but by the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> it was corrupted; &amp; by propagation, this corruption is diſtilled into all the parts of our mindes: ſo that it maketh vs guiltie of Gods wrath, and to bring forth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the fruits of the fleſh. <hi>Rom. 5.12.14. Gal. 5.19, 20, 21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is ſinne in generall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sinne is euerie tranſgreſſion of anie of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13766:27"/>
Commandements of the lawe of God, either in not doing them, or not doing them to their right end, or in not doing them ſo willingly, and fully as the Lawe requireth. <hi>Nehem. 1.7. 1. Ioh. 3.4. Iam. 2.8, 9. Rom. 7.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in ſoule. <hi>Matth. 22.37, 39.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in bodie. <hi>Matth. 5.28. Ro. 7.7, 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is it to be the childe of Gods wrath?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be ſubiect to the eternall curſe of God, which is the due reward of ſinne. <hi>Deut. 27.26. Gal. 3.10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the curſe of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is all the plagues that doo belong either to the ſoule or the bodie, which are comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the whole booke of God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for this life. <hi>Leu. 26.</hi> the whole, <hi>Deu. 28.</hi> the whole.</p>
            <p>Secondly, eternall perdition and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both of bodie and ſoule. <hi>Roman. 6.23. Matth. 25.41.42. Reuel. 21.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then of our ſelues and the diuell commeth
<pb facs="tcp:13766:28"/>
ſinne, and damnation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea verely; and of no other. <hi>Gene. 3.1,</hi> to <hi>8. Iohn 8.44. 1. Iohn. 3.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let vs come to the 5. point: tel me, how ſhal we come to the knowledge of our ſin &amp; miſerie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Onely by the perfect rule of the holy &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous law of God. <hi>Ro. 3.20.</hi> &amp; <hi>7.7. Gal. 3.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the Lawe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a moſt perfect rule, and a holie doctrine fined from all corruption, &amp; preſcribed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God himſelfe vnto vs; ſhewing, what we ought to doo, &amp; what not. <hi>Pſal. 12.6.</hi> &amp; <hi>19.7, 8, 9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in reſpect of God. <hi>Matt. 22 37.</hi> to <hi>40.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, in reſpect of our neibors. <hi>Matt. 22 37.</hi> to <hi>40.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doth the word of God deliuer all things, ſufficiently for the perfection of Chriſtianitie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea: &amp; that in this ſort. Firſt, for the pure ſeruice of God, which is true holineſſe. <hi>Deu. 13.32. Matth. 15.9. Iohn 4.24. Eſay 8.19,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13766:28"/>
20. Gal. 1.7, 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, for our ſaluation. <hi>Iohn 5.39. Ioh. 20.30, 31.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, for our ſufficient righteouſneſſe vnto men. <hi>2. Tim. 3.16, 17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maie wee not ſerue God after our owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions and traditions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No verelie: for, firſt our vnderſtanding is blindneſſe. <hi>1. Cor. 2.14. Iere. 10.14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, our wiſedome is fooliſhneſſe. <hi>1. Cor. 1.20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the ſame an enemie to the will and wiſedome of God. <hi>Rom. 8.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, They are accurſed that ſerue God with any other doctrine and wiſedome than his owne. <hi>Gal. 1.8. Reuel. 22.18, 19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where may wee finde a ſhort ſumme of the will of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ten Commandements: whereof the foure firſt belong vnto the firſt Table, &amp; the ſixe laſt vnto the ſecond Table.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:29"/>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore was it giuen in two Tables, and not rather in one?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, it was to ſhewe a flatte difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the dutie we owe to God, and the duetie we owe to our neighbours.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the firſt is more excellent, &amp; to be preferred before the ſecond. <hi>Mat. 6.33.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doo they that breake anie commandement of the firſt, offend greater than in breaking any of the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea verelie: for the firſt belongeth vnto God and his ſeruice; and the ſecond to men, &amp; their duties one towards another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But out Sauiour Chriſt ſeemeth to make them equall when he ſaith; <hi>Thou must loue God with all thy heart, with all thy ſoule, &amp;c. This is the first and greateſt Commandement: &amp; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is like vnto it, thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe.</hi> Matth. 22.31, 38, 39.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the latter is like vnto the former, not in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13766:29"/>
the excellencie and equalitie of matter: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath ſome affinitie and agreement with the firſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe each of them teacheth the true and perfect will of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as Loue is the fountain of al thoſe things, which belong vnto God comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the firſt Table; euen ſo the loue of our neighbor, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head of all thoſe things which are due vnto our neighbor, and is expreſſed in the ſecond Table. <hi>Mark. 12.29, 30, 31.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherfore is the ſecond Table preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the firſt, as appeareth by <hi>Hoſ. 6.7. Mat. 9.13.</hi> &amp; <hi>12.13.</hi> if they be not equal in excellencie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the Lord dooth thereby reproue hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, which eſpecially buſie themſelues with the outward ſeruice of God; but (void of all pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie, and their manners alienated from all inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie) the fruites of charitie and true righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is farre from them. <hi>Mich. 6.5, 6, 7, 8. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea. 6.6. Matth. 9.13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, herein he noteth his great care vnto mutuall loue in vs one towardes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, accounting it not to bee his ſeruice and
<pb facs="tcp:13766:30"/>
worſhip (although commanded) if the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that we owe to our neighbors be negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. <hi>1. Ioh. 3.15, 17.</hi> &amp; <hi>4.7, 8, 12. Eſa. 58.3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>May not the two Tables be ſeperated and plucked aſunder?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No verely, for they were ioined of God toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; therefore not to be ſeperated <hi>Mat. 19.6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What gather you thereby?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that it is not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for vs only to haue a ciuill honeſtie, &amp; buſie our ſelues in the ſecond Table; but alſo we muſt be religious &amp; exerciſe our ſelues in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt table. <hi>Deut. 6.5. Eph. 4.24. Tit. 2.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, not onely religious vnto our God: but alſo we muſt practiſe the ſecond ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; that is, to loue our neighbor, &amp; vſe hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of life. <hi>Eph. 4.24.25. Titus 2.11, 12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What if we do the one, &amp; neglect the other?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we doo the firſt and not the ſeconde, it is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13766:30"/>
but an outward holineſſe, which is hypocriſie. And to doo the ſecond and not the firſt, is but ciuill honeſtie, which is méere Atheiſme: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the one muſt goe with the other: that is, true godlineſſe and righteouſneſſe, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond muſt proceed out of the firſt, or els it is but a counterfet righteouſneſſe. <hi>Iere. 7.4, 5, 6, 9, 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why did hee write them in ſtone, and not in parchment, or after ſome other manner?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt to teach vs, that it ſerueth for al ages, as a doctrine of continuance, to be a perfect rule of righteouſneſſe. <hi>Pſal. 19.7, 8, 9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly to ſhew vs, that our heartes are ſtonie, before they are ſoftened by the Spirit of God. <hi>Ezek. 35.26, 27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that we muſt write them in our harts, to be our inſtructers, and counſellers. <hi>Pſal. 1.2.</hi> and <hi>119.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, it telleth vs, that vnleſſe the Lord write them in our harts, by the finger of his hand, all is but vaine. <hi>2. Cor. 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:31"/>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why was the Law giuen after ſo fearefull a manner; as by thundrings, lightnings, darknes, and ſhaking of heauen and earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was to driue, not onely the <hi>Iewes,</hi> but all other people of God vnto the end of the world, to haue it, firſt in great reuerence. <hi>Pſalm. 19.9. Eſay 66.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to heare it with great attentiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Eccl. 4.17. Matth 13.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, to practiſe it in al obedience. <hi>1. Sa. 15. 22, 23. Iere. 7.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why, would not wee els regard the Lawe of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No verelie: for ſuch is the corruption of our nature, that thoſe things which are <list>
                  <item>firſt, moſt eaſie;</item>
                  <item>ſecondlie, familiar; <hi>and</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>thirdly, not carrying with them a Maieſtie and power;</item>
               </list>
are contemned in our eyes: for which cauſe, God ſéeing the crookedneſſe of our Nature, did magnifie both his Lawe and Goſpell, with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13766:31"/>
wonderfull miracles, and fearefull ſignes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fixed in them great power and ſharpneſſe, to terrifie and ſtrike downe the froward and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious. <hi>Mark. 16.20. Heb. 2.4. 2. Cor. 10.4, 5, 6. Actes 2.5, 9, 10.</hi> and <hi>24.26.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By whom was the Lawe giuen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Angels, as the holie Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paule</hi> witneſſeth: wherein wee may ſee a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table commendation of the Lawe, to teach vs al holy obedience. <hi>Acts. 7.39. Gal. 3.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rehearſe thoſe commandements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God ſpake theſe words and ſaid, I am, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is the firſt (which is comprehended in theſe words, God ſpake, &amp;c.) a commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: but a preface or introduction to the lawe of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you out of the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt that God is the author of the lawe, and
<pb facs="tcp:13766:32"/>
therefore the ſame to be obeyed and loued. <hi>Ioh. 14.23. Pſalm. 119.97.103.136.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, how it is ſpirituall, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it teacheth vs to bee ſpirituallie minded. <hi>Ro 7.7, 14. Matth. 5.28. Iohn 4.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the might and maieſtie of God is ſet foorth in the ſame to teach his children to reuerence him with feare, and to terrifie the rebellious. <hi>Actes 5.5. Iere. 10.6, 10,</hi> to <hi>14. Exod. 20.18, 19. Deut. 4.10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the goodnes of God is expreſſed, in the children of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> their and our deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: theirs temporal &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a fleſhlie <hi>Pharao;</hi> but ours a ſpiritual <hi>Pharao,</hi> the diuel &amp; the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal bondage of hell: al which teach vs true thankfullnes. <hi>Exod. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13,</hi> &amp; <hi>14. cha. Ephe. 4.8. Heb. 2.14, 15. 1. Iohn. 3.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the firſt commandement, <hi>thou ſhalt haue no other Gods but me?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that there is but one onely true God to witt, the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Deu. 6.4. 1. Cor. 8.4, 6. Ephe. 4.5, 6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that I muſt worſhip him in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and trueth, onely in the mediatour Ieſus
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13766:32"/>
Chriſt. <hi>Iohn 4.24. Iohn 17.3.1. Timo. 2.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, wherein this worſhip of God doth conſiſt; (that is to ſay)</p>
            <p>Firſt, in louing him. <hi>Deut. 6.5.</hi> and <hi>30.16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in fearing him reuerently. <hi>Pſal. 34.9. 1. Pet. 1.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, in calling on him and praiſing him continuallie. <hi>Pſal. 50.14, 15. Math. 6.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, in yeelding him an holy obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. <hi>1. Sam. 15.22, 23. 1. Pet. 1.14, 15, 16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, in putting my whole truſt in his iuſtice, mercy, and power. <hi>Ieremy 17.7, 8. Actes 17.25, 26.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is loue towards God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a burning zeale proceeding from a pure heart in deſire to aduance the glory of God, in thought, word and works, according to his will commanded in his word. <hi>Exod. 32.32. Pſalm. 69.9. Iohn 2.17. Deut. 6.4, 5, 6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is reuerent feare?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a ſonnelike reuerence kindled in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harts of the faithfull, conſiſting vpon the reuerence of
<pb facs="tcp:13766:33"/>
God, being moſt iuſt, and the loue of him being moſt merciful, which is lightned by faith. <hi>Pſal. 130.4. Pſalme. 119.53. Iob. 1.2. Acts. 10.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is obedience?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a faithfull ſubmiſſion of the minde, whereby the word and will of the commander is obeyed without gainſaying, according to the ſtrength and ability, both in wll, in eare, in word and deede. <hi>1. Sam. 15.22, 23. Pſal. 40. Heb. 10. Ioh. 4. Matth. 7. Phil. 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the end of this commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lorde ſheweth vs, how hee alone, will haue the preheminence among his people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whie is it ſet in the firſt place?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This precept is not by order onely the firſt, but alſo ſuch as without the ſame, all the reſt be to no purpoſe; for therein is comprehended, the head of true religion, godlines, and iuſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you out of the ſecond comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13766:33"/>
                  <hi>thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Image, &amp;c.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in this commandement we are taught, how wee ſhould worſhip GOD purely with his Godhead of the holy Trinitie: for <list>
                  <item>Firſt, God is a ſpirit. <hi>Iohn. 4.24.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, inuiſible. <hi>1. Timo. 6.16, 17.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thirdly, incomprehenſible. <hi>Eſay. 66.2.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fourthly, infinite. <hi>Rom. 11.33, 34.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore not to bee purtraied &amp; not to make anie image of the Godhead.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deut. 4.15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 23, 24. Act. 17.29.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that he will be worſhipped in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and truth, and not by and with Images, nor by and in Angels, neither by or in any other cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature either men or women. <hi>Reuel. 19.10. Ioh. 4.24. Iere. 10.8. Heb. 2.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that God will not bee worſhipped, nor ſerued by the traditions, and framed ſeruice of man: for <hi>Matth. 15.9. Iere. 2.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, man is blinde in heauenly thinges. <hi>1. Cor. 2.14. Iho. 3.4, 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, fooliſh in Gods ſeruice. <hi>1. Cor. 1.20. Iere. 10.14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:34"/>Thirdly, an enemy to Gods pure worſhip. <hi>Rom. 8.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, God hateth all ſuch as ſhall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt his wiſdome with their owne inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and lying vanities, and loueth them that keepe his commandements and ſerue him with his owne waies. <hi>Galath. 2.7, 8. Iohn. 14.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the end of this commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is to worſhip GOD purely and holily, without mixture of prophane ſuperſtition ſuch as Idolatrie is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is Idolatrie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not onely the worſhipping of Images; but alſo the worſhipping of God with any fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſeruice, deuiſed of our corrupt witt; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, if wee giue his diuine honor and ſeruice to our ſelues, or any other creature, either to place them in ſteede of God, or to be equal with God. <hi>Iere. 2.13, 27, 28. Math. 15.9. Ephe. 5.5. Phil. 3.18, 19. Gal. 4.8. Iohn 9. Iohn 5.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:13766:34"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the third commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>thou ſhalt not take thy name of the Lord thy God in vaine, &amp;c?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, to reuerence his holy name, as his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, goodnes, power, works, iuſtice, and word. <hi>Pſalme 106.47. Pro. 18.10. 2. Chro. 29.10, 11, 12, 13. Leuit. 25.31, 32. 1. Timo. 6.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to vſe the holy name of God in an oath, moſt godly, carefullie, and feareful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not to ſweare lightly, raſhly, and falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but in lawfull cauſes, being lawfully cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thereunto by ſuch as haue authoritie. <hi>Exod. 22.10, 11. Iere. 4.2. Leuit. 19.12.</hi> and <hi>24.10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16. Leuiticus 6.13. Eſay 48.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, not to ſweare by creatures and i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous oathes, for GOD will not hold them guiltles, that doo abuſe his name, either raſhely, falſely, or by counterfeite oathes. <hi>Iere. 5.7. Amo. 8.14. Zepha. 1.4, 5. Pſal. 16.4. Ioſhua. 33.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, that wee vſe not the name of God to thoſe blaſphemous arts, as ſorceries,
<pb facs="tcp:13766:35"/>
charmings, coniurings, and ſuch like; neither yet to ſeeke to ſuch damned wretches, leaſt we bring eternall death vpon our ſelues. <hi>Le. 19.31.</hi> and <hi>20, 6, 27. 1. Cro. 10.10, 13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the end of this commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Gods name in an othe, in his worde, works, Sacraments; mercie, Iuſtice, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, might bee reuerenced, hallowed, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelie accounted of, by vs and all his people. <hi>Le. 20.7, 8. 1. Pet. 3.15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is an oath?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a reuerent and a ſerious calling God to witnes, either to confirme the trueth I ſpeak, or to puniſh me, if I ſpeake vntrueth. <hi>Ioſua. 9.19. Heb. 6.16, 17, 18. 2. Cor. 1.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the fourth commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Remember that thou keepe holy, &amp;c.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that we are ſtraightly charged, to kéepe holy the Sabaoth, in holines and righteouſnes.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13766:35"/>
               <hi>Leuit. 19.30. Ezek. 20.19, 20. Eſay 56.4, 5, 6,</hi> and <hi>58, 13, 14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, not to prophane the ſame in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, carding, bowling, ſhooting, gaming, dauncing, drinking, gadding from place to place, feaſting, bargaining, buing, ſelling, beare bayting, traueling, turmoyling in our earthlie affaires and ſuch like. <hi>Iere. 17.21,</hi> to the end. <hi>Eze. 20.12, 13. Nehe. 13.15,</hi> to <hi>23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, what the exerciſes of the Sabaoth ſhould be, which ought to be theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to heare Gods word preached, with great reuerence and attentiuenes: to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, and reade the ſame carefully; and to talke thereof with all godlines. <hi>Pſalme. 1.2. Luke. 4.16, 17, 18. Acts. 13.14, 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that we make our praiers vnto God with great zeale and that: <hi>Matth. 6.9.</hi> and <hi>18.19. Pſal. 68.26. 2. Cor. 24.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, for his glorie.</item>
               <item>Secondly, for our ſelues.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, for his church.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Thirdly, to receaue the Sacraments hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie and thanckfullie thereby. <hi>Actes 2.24. Acts. 20.7, 8, 9, 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort our conſciences. <hi>1. Cor. 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:36"/>Secondly, to confirm our faith. <hi>Ro. 4.11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, to viſite and diſtribute, to the ſick, lame, poore, and aged:
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, cherefullie. <hi>Acts. 2.46. 1. Cor. 16.1, 2. Gal. 6.10. 2. Cor. 9.7. Phil. 2.14. 1. Pet. 4.9, 10. Math. 25.31, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, diligentlie. <hi>Acts. 2.46. 1. Cor. 16.1, 2. Gal. 6.10. 2. Cor. 9.7. Phil. 2.14. 1. Pet. 4.9, 10. Math. 25.31, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thirdly, liberallie. <hi>Acts. 2.46. 1. Cor. 16.1, 2. Gal. 6.10. 2. Cor. 9.7. Phil. 2.14. 1. Pet. 4.9, 10. Math. 25.31, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is a Sabaoth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a reſt and ceaſing from all ſeruile and vncleane works. <hi>Eſay 58.13, 14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who muſt keepe the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not onely parents, gouernours of common weales, and priuate families; but alſo the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, ſonnes and daughters, with men and maid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruants, yea, the very ſtrangers and none ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. <hi>Deut. 4.14, 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the end thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:13766:36"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Onely this? That we might auoide all cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and be mainteyned in all feare and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence of God; and rightlie meditate on his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall kingdome, and our endles reſt in Chriſt. <hi>Ezek. 20.29, 20.</hi> and <hi>22.8.26. Eſay 66.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learneſt thou in the fift commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>honour thy father and thy mother; &amp;c?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, we are taught, to honor, loue, feare, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey and reuerence, our naturall Parents, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, gouernors, Maſters, Paſtours and el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lders. <hi>Leuit. 19.3. Gene. 4.5, 6, 10, 11.</hi> and <hi>46.29. 1. Sam. 22.3, 4. Prou. 30.17. Exod. 21.17. Ephe. 6.1, 2, 3. Rom. 13.1,</hi> to <hi>8. 1. Tim. 2.1, 2, 3. 1. Theſ. 5.12, 13. Heb. 13.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to loue, inſtruct, cheriſh, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our inferiours.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in reſpect of the ſoule, as: <list>
                  <item>Firſt in ſpirituall inſtructions. <hi>Ephe. 6.4. Col. 18.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly the foode of life. <hi>Pſal. 78.5, 6, 7. Iohn. 6.68.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thirdly, a godly gouerning. <hi>1. Theſ. 1.6, 8, 9. Titus. 2.1, 2, 3, 4.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:37"/>Secondly, in reſpect of the bodie, as</p>
            <p>Firſt, in good gouernement. <hi>Heb. 12.9,</hi> to <hi>10.23.13, 14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in feeding the bodie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in clothing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. <hi>1. Tim. 5.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The godlie oft times die in their youth, and the wicked liue vntill old age: how then is the promiſe fullfilled, and God iuſt in not puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vngodly, liue (in their proſperitie) in an accurſed eſtate, and to their greater vengeance: But the godly liue, ſo farre foorth as it ſhall be to Gods glorie and their ſaluation. <hi>Eſay. 57.1, 2. Eccle. 8.8.10, 11, 12, 13. Pro. 16.31. Pſalm. 37.35.</hi> to <hi>40.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is honor?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To honor, is to obey, reuerence, and to be du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull vnto the ordinance of God, as vnto God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the end of this commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:13766:37"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord hath appoynted decrees, and an order, which he will not haue to be taken away, or reſiſted, by ſtubbornnes and vnthankfulnes; but to be reuerenced and obeyed of vs. <hi>1. Pet. 2.13.</hi> to <hi>21. Pro. 14.21, 22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the ſixt commandement, <hi>thou ſhalt doo no murther?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, we are forbidden to murther in heart: as raſh anger, hatred, and enuie. <hi>Leuit. 19.16, 17. Matth. 5.21, 22. Ephe. 4.16. 1. Iohn 3.15. Col. 3.8. Iam. 3.14, 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in the tongue: as in giuing euill counſell, raſh iudgement, ſlaundering, and mocking. <hi>Matth. 5.22,</hi> and <hi>7.1, 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, by the hand: as in ſhedding inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud, either vnlawfullie in iudgement, or wilfullie in fighting, and in vniuſt warres. <hi>Gene. 9.6. Reuel. 13.10. Matth. 26.52. Eſa. 1.21, 22. Ezek. 1.22.27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, alſo wee are thereby ſtraightlie commanded ſo to loue our neighbours: as;</p>
            <p>Firſt, in heart, and with all patience to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, and beare with the infirmities of them.
<pb facs="tcp:13766:38"/>
               <hi>Ephe. 4.2, 3, 4. Ro. 12.10, 19. Gal. 6.1, 2, 3, 4. Matth. 5.44, 45. 1. Pet. 4.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to giue them good counſel and to preſerue their good names. <hi>1. Theſſa. 5.11. Heb. 10.24, 25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, in comforting, helping, and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them in their neceſſities and great miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. <hi>Eſa. 58.6, 7. 1. Pet. 4.9, 10. Matth. 25.34.</hi> to the end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the end of this commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord hath knit togeather by a certaine vnſeperable vnitie all mankind: ſo that the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all, ought to be committed to euery one, and therefore all violence, and murther, ought to be auoided of vs all. <hi>Eſa. 58.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.12. Ephe. 4.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is murther?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the vnlawful taking away the life &amp; good name of any man, by what euil meanes ſo euer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the ſeauenth commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>thou ſhalt not commit adulterie?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:13766:38"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſame; firſt, wee are forbidden all manner of whoredome, as inceſt, fornication, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie, rapes, and buggeries, in hart, in word, in countenance, and in act. <hi>Math. 5.28. Leuit. 18.</hi> and <hi>20.10, 11, 12. 1. Cor. 5.1. Ephe. 5.3, 4, 5, 6. 2. Theſ. 4.3, 4, 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the contrarie is required of vs, as chaſte hearts, chaſte lookes, chaſte talke, and all thoſe good meanes that ſhall increaſe &amp; nouriſh theſe things in vs, as faſting, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, ſobrietie, and modeſtie in apparrell, in our behauiour and in our diet. <hi>1. Cor. 7.2, 3.4, 5. Heb. 13.4. Ephe. 4.29, 30.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is adulterie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a ſinne againſt the ordinance of God, and the couenant of true loue, made the one to the other, whereby the huſband goeth to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther woman, or the wife vnto another man to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file their bodies, and make them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, which indéede are not their owne but their mates ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by holy wedlock. <hi>1. Cor. 7.4.</hi> and <hi>6.15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the end of this commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:39"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Almightie God, who is purenes it ſelfe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth onely in purenes, and therefore hee would haue vs to abandon all vncleanes, and to liue chaſtlie and purely. <hi>1. Theſ. 4.7. 1. Pet. 14, 15, 16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the ſixth commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? <hi>thou ſhalt not ſteale?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I am forbidden all theft, as violence, extortion, cruelties, vſuries, briberies, deceipts and coſinage. <hi>Leuit. 19.11, 13. Exod. 21.16. Leuit. 19.15. Iere. 15.10. Pſal. 15.5. Ezek. 18.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in thought.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in word. <hi>1. Theſ. 4.6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, in all our actions. <hi>Pro. 11.1.</hi> and <hi>16.11. Exod. 22.1. Ephe. 5.4, 28.1. Cor. 10.</hi> and <hi>6.9, 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I am commanded to deale iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with al men, and to preſerue that which is theirs; to lend freelie without gaine: to deale plainely in bargayning: and not to be bribed to preuent iuſtice and iudgement. <hi>Leuit. 25.35, 36. Luke 6.35. Exod. 21.33, 34.35,</hi> and <hi>22.6.</hi> to <hi>16. Matth. 7.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:13766:39"/>Thirdly, to labor for my liuing; to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with my eſtate: and to be helpfull to others to my power. <hi>Ephe. 4.28. 2. Theſ. 3.10. Gene. 3.16. Phil. 4.11, 12. 1. Timo. 6.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is theft?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a violent and deceitfull taking away of another mans goods, moueable, or vnmouable, againſt the good wil of the right owner, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his knowledge, not reſtoring the ſame. <hi>Gen. 31.19, 30. Eſay 1.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the end of this commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God who is onely perfect iuſt, abhorreth all vnrighteouſnes: and teacheth vs to giue euery man his owne, in iuſtice and equitie. <hi>Titus. 2.11, 12. Zopha. 1.9. Romans. 13.8.9.10. Zacha. 5.2, 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the ninth commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? <hi>thou ſhalt not beare falſe witnes against thy neighbour?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:40"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I am forbidden all falſe witnes bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, either priuately, or publiquely, all lying, carieng of tales, and falſe ſlanders; alſo not to heare them, much leſſe to beleeue them, but ſharpelie to rebuke them. <hi>Leuit. 19.5.9. Iere. 9.3, 4, 5. Iohn 8.44.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I am taught to ſpeake the truth vprightly, both priuately and publiquely and not to lie for any matter, either for the glorie of God, or for the ſafetie of our owne liues or our neighbours. <hi>Epheſians 4.25. Colloſ. 3.9, 10. Romans 3.7, 8. Prouer. 12.22. Actes. 5.3, 4, 9, 20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſeeing a good name is pretious; therefore not to ſlaunder the ſame, but to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer our brethrens infirmities through loue: and beſides not to giue any occaſion our ſelues to be ſlandered. <hi>Pſal. 15.1.3. Eccle. 7.3. Pro. 22.1. 1. Cor. 13.6. 1. Pet. 4.8. Mat. 18.6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is falſe witnes bearing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An vniuſt accuſation, laid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any man, either of words or works, which were neuer ſpoken nor don. <hi>1. Kin. 27.12.13. Mat. 26.60.61.62.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:13766:40"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the end of this commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord our God: who is trueth it ſelfe, hateth all kinde of lying; and therefore would, that we ſhould eſpecially haue a care to ſpeake the trueth. <hi>Pro. 13, 5.</hi> and <hi>12, 22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the tenth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement? <hi>thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours houſe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, it dooth not only condemne &amp; reſtraine the ſettled thoughts in our hearts, from that which is euill, but alſo the light &amp; vaniſhing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of euil: <hi>Ro. 7.7. Tit. 2.12. 1. Pet. 2.11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it teacheth vs to be watchfull o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all our thoughts, and to mortefie them leaſt they take roote, and become mightie and huge trées, bringing foorth monſterous fruits of wickednes. <hi>Col. 3.5. Romans. 12.2. Ephe. 4.22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, it teacheth vs, to ſéeke after hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly thoughts, and godly deſires, and ſo to cheriſh them, by hearing, reading, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating of Gods word, and by praier. <hi>Ephe. 4.23, 24. Pſal. 1.2,</hi> &amp; <hi>119.1, 2. Pro. 2.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:41"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is concupiſcence?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a motion of the minde (procéeding out of our corrupt nature) which dooth luſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt the lawe of nature, whereby we are ſtirred vp to wickednes, although wee giue no conſent thereunto and commit no euill thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Rom. 7.23. Gal. 5.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the end of this commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our good God, who is moſt pure, will haue the whole minde poſſeſſed with puritie, and the affections of loue.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, vnto God himſelfe.</item>
               <item>Secondly, to our brethren.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, that all luſt which is contrarie to a true and pure loue, muſt bee expelled out of our minde. <hi>Matth. 22 37, 38. Rom. 12.2. 1. Theſ. 4.4, 5, 7.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now let vs come vnto the laſt point, can we fulfill this holy and pure lawe of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No verely: and that becauſe</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:13766:41"/>Firſt, our wiſdome is both fooliſhnes, and an enemie to the lawe of God. <hi>Iere. 20.24. Rom. 8.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe of the corruption of our nature which continuallie rebelleth againſt the lawe of God. <hi>Romans. 7.14.</hi> to the end. <hi>Gal. 5.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe of our ſelues wee cannot think a good thought, nor ſpeake a good word, much leſſe doo good works. <hi>2. Cor. 3.4, 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, becauſe that although we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, and ſanctified; yet our faith is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, and ſubiect to ſinne. <hi>1. Cor. 13.9.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seeing wee come to the knowledge of our ſinnes, by the lawe of God; ſhall wee therefore reiect and caſt away the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God forbid: for the lawe is good, perfect, and holy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore then, ſerueth the lawe, and what is it? <hi>Pſal. 19.7, 8, 9. Rom. 7.12. 1. Timo. 1.8.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, it is a glaſſe to ſhewe vs both our
<pb facs="tcp:13766:42"/>
ſinnes and miſeries, thereby to pull downe our fooliſh pride. <hi>Iam. 1.23, 24, 25. Rom, 3.19, 20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, a ſchoolemaſter to bring vs to Chriſt. <hi>Gal. 3.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, a rule of righteouſnes to teach vs to liue well. <hi>Pſal. 1.2, 3.</hi> and <hi>119.1, 2, 3, 4, 9. Pro. 2.10.</hi> to <hi>20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sith we cannot keepe the lawe, and ſo not be iuſtified by the works of the lawe, why ſhould we do good works?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt to teſtifie our loue and ready obedience vnto our good God and louing father. <hi>Mal. 1.6. Iohn 14, 21. 1. Pet. 1.14.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to win our bretheren to Chriſt. <hi>Iam. 5.19, 20. 1. Pet. 2.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, by them muſt wee ſtoppe the mouthes of the aduerſaries of Chriſt, and the trueth, which are without. <hi>Col. 4.5, 6. 1. Pet. 4.14, 15, 16, 17. Phil. 2.14, 15, 16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, by them we muſt make our elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſure to our ſelues, as the onely fruits of a liuely faith in Chriſt, whereby wee are iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified and ſaued. <hi>2. Pet. 1.8, 10. Phil. 2.12, 13. Gal. 2.16.20.</hi> and <hi>3.14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:13766:42"/>Fifthly, by them we muſt comfort and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh the poore and miſerable people. <hi>Matth. 25.34, 35, 36, &amp;c. Eſay 58.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How many things belong vnto good works?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, they muſt be ruled by the liue of Gods word. <hi>Deut. 4.2. Matth. 28.20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, proceede from a true and ſounde faith. <hi>Rom. 14.23. Heb. 11.16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, be free from all hipocriſie, vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorie, diſcerning, and ſuch like, and onely be done to the glorie of God. <hi>Matth. 6.1, 2, 3, 4. Matth. 5.16. 1. Pet. 2.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who muſt put good works in our hearts, and frame vs there vnto?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Onely God, our Creator and Sauior, for he it is that muſt giue vs,</p>
            <p>Firſt, a right vnderſtanding of his will <hi>1. Cor. 2.12, 13. Iam. 1.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, a true faith in his word, and mercies in Chriſt. <hi>Epheſ. 2.8, 9, 10. Iohn 6.29.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, true humilitie, zeale, and power
<pb facs="tcp:13766:43"/>
to ſet foorth his glorie. <hi>Phil. 2.12, 13. 2. Cor. 3.4, 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let vs come to the third parte of this article, namely, how God preſerueth the worlde with all his creatures: and tell mee, how dooſt thou prooue the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The holy ſcripture aſſureth and teacheth me, how that God onely with his mightie power, in his diuine wiſdome, giueth life, ſtrength, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, generation, and continuance vnto his creatures; and the huge maſſe of the earth other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, they and it would ſoone come to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Gene. 1.1, 2. Pſal. 104.29, 30. Heb. 1.2, 3. Gene. 1.</hi> the whole.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What haue wee to learne in this part?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the great power of God in vpholding and mainteyning all things. <hi>Iere. 10.10, 11, 12, 13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, his vnſpeakeable wiſdome, not onely in creating all things, ſo excellently, and beutifullie, but alſo in that ſame wiſdome, hee keepeth and preſerueth them. <hi>Heb. 1.2, 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:13766:43"/>Thirdly, his goodnes in doing thoſe things for the ſonnes of men. <hi>Pſalm. 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the vſe of this doctrine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, a reuerent feare of his power. <hi>Iere. 5.22, 23, 24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, an admiration, and praiſing the greatneſſe of his wiſedome. <hi>Pſal. 104.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, a true and continuall thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for his mercies, and a reuerent vſing of his creatures. <hi>Pſal. 103.1, 2, 3, 4.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom. 11.36. 1. Cor. 10.31. 1. Tim. 4.1, 2, 3, 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now let vs come to the laſt part, to wit of Gods prouidence, and tell me what it is?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the foreknowledge, eternall decree, and appointment of the almightie, wiſe, and holie God: of all the affaires and actions that ſhould be done, from the beginning of the worlde vnto the ende thereof either of good or euill; as An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, men, diuells, or anie other creature what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How proueſt thou, that God ſoreknoweth
<pb facs="tcp:13766:44"/>
all things, before they come to paſſe, &amp; whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he hath appointed ſhall come to paſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That he foreknoweth all things, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he hath appointed in his vnchaungeable decree to be done, either in creation, redemption ſaluation, or gouernment, theſe places of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture moſt effectually doo proue. <hi>Eſa. 7.14. Matt. 1.22, 23. Mich. 5.2. Matt. 2.1.2. 1. Pet. 2.19, 20, 21. 2. Ti. 1.9.</hi> &amp; <hi>2.19. act. 19.48. Eſay. 46.10. Pſal. 239.15, 16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How dooſt thou prooue, that hee ruleth all things, and all his creatures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That God doth rule al creatures, is proued. <hi>Pſa. 115.3.</hi> &amp; <hi>113.7, 8, 9.</hi> &amp; <hi>147.</hi> &amp; <hi>107.</hi> &amp; <hi>104.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What order wilt thou keepe in this point?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, how he ruleth al the creatures in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Secondly, all the creatures on earth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, all puniſhments and plagues.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, all the Creatures in the ſeas.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, all the diuels and vncleane ſpirits.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:13766:44"/>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proceede to the firſt part?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe in heauen are.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Angels. <hi>Pſal. 81.11, 12, 13. Heb. 1.14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, thunder. <hi>1. Sam. 12.18. Exo. 20.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Windes. <hi>Num. 11.31. Iona. 1.4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, lightnings. <hi>Ier. 10.13. Exo. 20.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, raine. <hi>Ier. 10, 13. Pſal. 147.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, Snow. <hi>pſal. 147.16.</hi> and <hi>148.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seuenthly, haile. <hi>Ioſh. 10.11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eightly, Sonne, Moone, and ſtarres. <hi>Ioſh. 10.12, 13, 14. Eſa. 38.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proceed to the ſecond: that God ruleth all the creatures vpon and in earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then to the mouing creatures, as of one kind.</p>
            <p>Firſt al men generally. <hi>Pro. 26.1, 9, 7.</hi> &amp; <hi>20.24. Ier. 10.13. Pſa. 33.16. acts. 17.28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, particularly of good &amp; euil men: as,
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, in all good actions. <hi>1. Cor. 4.7. 2. cor. 3.4, 5. Iam. 1.17. Ephe. 2.9. Geneſ. 40.1.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, in their euill actions. <hi>Iudg. 7.22. 2. cron. 20. Gen. 50.20.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:13766:45"/>Thirdly, more particularly, as:
<list>
                        <item>Firſt, Princes, <hi>Pſa. 6.15.7.8. Pro. 8.15.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Secondly, Nobles and Senators. <hi>Eſa. 3.1, 2, 3, 4.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Thirdly, Iudges. <hi>Pro. 8.16.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Fourthly, ſubiects. <hi>1. Sam. 10.26.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Fiftly, enemies. <hi>Pro. 16.7.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Sixtly, Warres both to raiſe and ceaſe. <hi>Iudg. 9.23, 24.25. pſal. 46.9.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Then to mouing creatures of other kindes, as: <list>
                  <item>Firſt, al manner of cattle, as oxen, horſes, ſheepe, &amp;c. <hi>Gen. 2.19, 20.</hi> &amp; <hi>7.1.</hi> to <hi>11.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, lions. <hi>1. Reg. 13.24.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thirdly, beares. <hi>2. Reg. 2.24.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fourthly, frogges. <hi>Exod. 6.12.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fiftly, flies. <hi>Exod. 8.22.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sixtly, lice. <hi>Exod. 8.17.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Seuenthly wormes. <hi>Ioel 1.4. Iona. 4.7.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Eightly, ſerpents. <hi>Num. 21.6.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Ninthly, hornets. <hi>Ioſh. 24.12.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Tenthly, rauens and ſparrowes. <hi>1. Reg. 17.4.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Now for al creatures that grow, and are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moouable, hauing their being on, &amp; in the earth, I will touch them: but firſt beginning with the Earth it ſelfe: for which this is my proofe.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13766:45"/>
               <hi>Gen. 1.12, 13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, trees. <hi>Matth. 19.19, 20. Iona. 4.6, 7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, hearbes, flowers, graſſe, &amp; corne. <hi>Pſal. 104.14. Matth. 6.28, 29, 30.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proceede now vnto the third point, and tell me how thou canſt proue that all plagues and puniſhments come from God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The holy ſcripture ſheweth, how that there commeth no euil vnto a Citie, vnleſſe that God doo ſende the ſame: it is hee that killeth and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth life, and bringeth downe vnto the graue; he maketh poore, and bringeth lowe: yea, neither the peſtilence, conſumption, feauer, burning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, feruent heat, mildeaw, ſword, blaſting, boc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, emeroides, ſcabbe, itch, madnes, blindnes, a mans wife defiled, a mans houſe &amp; vineyeard taken away, dearth, famine, captiuitie, graſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers &amp; worms to deſtroy the fruits of the earth, hunger, thirſt, nakedneſſe, to eate the fruites of the wombe, and ſuch like, nor anie elſe can hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, except the Lord ſend them: ſo that they neither come by chance, or through ouerſight, or anie other way but by Gods prouidence and
<pb facs="tcp:13766:46"/>
appointment. <hi>Leuit. 26. Deut. 28. Exod. 8.9.</hi> &amp; <hi>10.</hi> chap. <hi>1. Sam. 2.6, 7, 8. Amos 3.6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proceede vnto the 4. point: that God ruleth all the creatures in the ſea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will, and therein proue that he ruleth: <list>
                  <item>Firſt, the ſea it ſelfe. <hi>Exod. 14, 16. Ioſh. 3.14, 15, 16, 17.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, the fiſhes in the ſea. <hi>Iona. 1.17.</hi> &amp; <hi>2.10. Matt. 17.27. Luk. 5, 6, 7, 8.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thirdly, the foules thereof. <hi>Gen. 7.</hi> &amp; <hi>8.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proceede vnto the 5. and laſt point, &amp; tel me how ye proue that God ruleth the diuels of hel?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will effectually doo the ſame: for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, theſe places of Scripture doo affirm and proue his dominion and rule ouer them, and of them. <hi>Iob. 1.</hi> and <hi>2. 1. Sam. 16.14. 1. Re. 21.20,</hi> to <hi>23. Ma. 8.31, 32. Act. 16.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, if he were not tied by the power of God, he would ſoone deſtroy and deuoure vs. <hi>1. Pet. 5.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſaiſt, that God ruleth the planets, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13766:46"/>
the firmament, with all things therein?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is moſt true.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea: but doo they not ſerue for times and ſeaſons, to rule &amp; diſpoſe man in all his affairs, as ſickneſſe, health, life and death, &amp; in al good lucke and bad lucke beſides?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Farre be it from all good Chriſtians once to thinke ſo, but much more to beleeue, &amp; affirme the thing: for it is very ſorcerie and ſoothſaying.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What els is it when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, they are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for times, &amp; ſeaſons, daies, &amp; yeres?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is moſt true that he ſaith ſo: but he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth nothing leſſe than ſuch a curſed aſtrologie: his meaning is onely, for things belonging to naturall and politicke order,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What meaneſt thou by this word, naturall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Winter and ſummer, ſowing time, reaping, planting, graffing, gardening, mowing, and all tilling.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:47"/>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What meaneſt thou by this word, politique?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reckoning of yeares, daies, &amp; months, as ſome from the creation of the world, ſome from Chriſtes incarnation, and ſome from one daie, and ſome from another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea, but earthly things, &amp; inferiour bodies, haue a kinde of affinitie and kindred with the courſe of the ſtarres, and ſo come by their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and qualitie, and ſo may be tolde (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ruled by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) what ſhall become of them, and what things ſhal happen vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the planets, and ſtarres?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although it be granted, that there is ſuch af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitie and kindred; yet to conclude therefore, that we may gather what ſhal befall vnto man, either in good lucke or badde, health or ſickneſſe, life or death: and what qualities, and diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he ſhall be of, and what death he ſhall die, it is moſt wicked; for theſe things belong onely to God, and are moſt vncertaine to men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What reaſons moueth thee thus to thinke?</hi>
            </p>
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:13766:47"/>Theſe: firſt for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one of their chiefeſt grounds is vncertaine, as the time of bearing to the time of conception; as:</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is a thing altogether impoſſible to haue a certaine knowledge of the verie time of begetting.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the time of birth, is not onely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes ſooner than it ſhould be, (thorough ſome occaſion offred) but alſo through weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the woman, ſhee oftentimes, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a longer time, or thorough long labour, ſhee miſſeth often times (not a minute) but houres, yea dayes; ſo that in the meane time, there is a very great inclination, and moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the heauens and Starres.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſeeing they that are borne at one minute and the ſelfe ſame inſtant of time, are commonly altogether;</p>
            <p>Firſt, vnlike in nature and manners.</p>
            <p>Secondly, doo die one before another, ſome one death, ſome another, ſome are poore, and ſome rich, and ſome in authority, and ſome of lowe degree.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that the force of ſeed, which is the matter whereof the childe is begotten and bred in the wombe, is greter than the force of
<pb facs="tcp:13766:48"/>
Starres, concerning the framing of man, to manners and nature; as we may ſee children to imitate their parents in naturall things; (ſeeing this, I ſay) it cannot bee rightly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the nature of the Planets and courſes of Starres.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What euills doo they commit by theſe their ſouthſayings, in attributing the gouernement of man vnto the Planets, and conſtellation of Starres?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, if good lucke hang vpon the Starres, then our holy obedience vnto God doth depend vpon them too; for this is the proper cauſe of that; and ſo we ſhall make the holy Ghoſt a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for he ſaieth; that euery good and perfect gifte commeth of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if the kinde of death, and euill luck (as they cal it) do hang vpon the ſtarres, then ſhall ſinne depende vpon them too: for of ſinne commeth all puniſhments, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together fooliſh and wicked to bee ſo attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for it commeth of the diuell and of our ſelues. <hi>Math. 15.19. 1. Ioh. 38.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, they herein make the ſtarres par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13766:48"/>
of the diuine nature and power of God, in that they ſay they gouerne and beare rule ouer mankinde, to direct them in al their affaires, and life, and death. <hi>Iob. 14.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, in this, they both raſhly enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſecrets of God, and alſo, as Gods they determine what ſhall come to paſſe.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, they are deceiuers, and bewitchers of the people that ſo teach, and therefore God will ſet himſelfe againſt them, and they are worthie to die the death. <hi>Le. 20.6.27. Deut. 15.7. Eſay. 44.25. Mala. 3.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Can the diuell and his inchanters, raiſe vp windes, ſtormes, lightnings and raine, when, where, and againſt whome it ſhall pleaſe them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No verely: for it is the Lord onely that hath power of theſe things, for they are in his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure houſe, and at his beck and commandement, either to defend and preſerue his people, or to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and deſtroy the wicked and reprobate. <hi>Pſal. 104.4. Exod. 9.23, 24, 25, 26.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is written in <hi>Iob,</hi> that the deuill did cauſe Lightnings, and raiſed vp winds? <hi>Iob. 1.16, 19.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:49"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true: but it was Gods permiſſion: for when as God worketh by ſathan and vſeth his ſeruice, the diuell worketh by the lightnings and windes, and that by the iuſt iudgement of God, to deceiue and harden the hearts of the people, becauſe they will not beleeue and receaue the truth: alſo herein, a notable crafte of ſatan may be ſeen, in that he conueyeth himſelf into winds and tempeſts, therby to make the world beléeue he is the author thereof: otherwiſe, God is the author of all windes, tempeſt and lightnings, as we haue already prooued. <hi>2. Theſ. 2.10.11.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What ſaieſt thou of the inchanters of Egipt which did great wonders &amp; merueilous things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the ſequell of their actions, and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions be marked, we ſhal ſee that neither they themſelues, nor their great maſter ſatan, can do more than God doth giue them leaue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why? what maketh thee ſo to ſay?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The knowledge of theſe things: that,</p>
            <p>Firſt, they could not turne the duſt into lice,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13766:49"/>
as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, but confeſſed that it was the power of God. <hi>Exod. 8.17, 18, 19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, they could not ſtand before <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> the ſeruant of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had done their falſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles in ſhewe, they could not vndo them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. <hi>Ezod. 7.21.</hi> to the end and <hi>8, 7, 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, neither could they vndo the true and powerfull miracles of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf, was faine with praier to vndo them. <hi>Exod. 8.12, 13. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why could not theſe incha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ters turne the duſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lice (as wel as to turn their rods into ſerpents, the riuers into bloud, and to bring forth froggs) it being a baſe thing in compariſon of the other?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in that they did the former things; it was by permiſſion of God, to harden the heart of <hi>Pharao,</hi> and to deceiue him with his people, that they might not let <hi>Iſraell</hi> goe (without the mightie hand of God) to their own deſtruction. <hi>Exod. 9.16. Rom. 9.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that the power of God in their deſtruction might be made knowne and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, vnto the whole world, and his faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:13766:50"/>
might be declared vnto all ages. <hi>Gene. 15.13, 14, 15, 16. Mica. 5.3, 4, 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that God might after a while in ſuffering them to doo great miracles in ſhew, confounde their wiſdomes in baſe and vile things, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world might ſee the falſehood &amp; wickednes of inchanters &amp; ſorcerers <hi>Mal. 3.5</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What think you of this opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; that the deuil &amp; inchanters haue no power, vpon that bodie or ſubſtance which is leſſe than a barley come?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think the ſame to be moſt vaine; and cleane againſt reaſon, for if they haue power ouer great things, they haue alſo power ouer ſmall things: but not the contrarie; as becauſe they haue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer ſmall things, therefore they haue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer great things: but in that they could not haue power ouer the duſt to make lice, it was becauſe, neither the diuell nor his inſtruments, haue power of themſelues, to do any thing, more than the will of God dooth permit and ſuffer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In thy proofe of the definition of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, thou ſaieſt that God ruleth al the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men; not onely the good, but alſo the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13766:50"/>
wherein what els dooſt thou? But make God the author of euill, which may not be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God forbid, we ſhould ſay, that God were the author of ſinne: for there is no euill with him, neither yet loueth he wickednes. <hi>Pſalm. 5.4.</hi> for perfect is the worke of almightie God, for al his waies are iudgement: God is true without wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes: iuſt and righteous is he. <hi>Deut. 42.4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why then? what doſt thou meane when thou ſaieſt, that God ruleth the euil actions of men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſay, that ſathan and our fleſh, are the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of ſinne, but yet on the other ſide, wee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme according to the Scriptures, that euen ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than and the wicked, are ſo bridled and ruled by the power and prouidence of God, that they doo not, nay cannot doo that euill, when, where, and againſt whom they would; for they all ſhal come to naught and to ruin, but what the Lords will &amp; appointment is, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe, whoſe will they execute in their wicked doings. <hi>Iob. 1. Gene. 50.20. 1. King. 13.4. 2. Sam. 17.14, 23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why? then God is the author of their ſinne,
<pb facs="tcp:13766:51"/>
and they without fault?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay not ſo, but he is moſt iuſt and perfect righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous; and yet they, wicked and vnholy in doing the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By reaſon of the diuers ends and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As how?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God doth it to ſet forth his glory, &amp; to bring forth the malice of his enemies, to ſhew it to all the world, that he may be iuſtified in his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and holy iudgements vpon them: alſo to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe his children by them and ſuch like: but the wicked and ſathan dooth the ſame of ſet malice, wilfully &amp; preſumptuouſly againſt God and his ſaints, and not willingly, and obediently to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie the counſell and purpoſe of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Canſt thou giue mee examples out of the Scripture for this matter? Where both GOD and the wicked haue delt in the ſame action: ſo that God is ſaid, to haue done that, which (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding)
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13766:51"/>
the wicked do?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea verely: as</p>
            <p>Firſt, of <hi>Iob,</hi> who confeſſeth that his cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities come of the Lord: yet Sathan &amp; the <hi>Sabaeans</hi> did worke in this action. <hi>Iob. 1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Dauid;</hi> who confeſſed that God ſtirred vp <hi>Shimei</hi> to curſe him: yet he did the ſame by the inſtigation of Sathan, and of a malicious purpoſe. <hi>2. Sam. 16.10, 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly it is ſaide; that God did ſtirre vp <hi>Dauid</hi> to number the people: yet it is ſaid in another place, that Satan prouoked him. <hi>2. Sam. 24.1. 1. Chro. 21.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is ſaid; that God ſent into the mouthes of the falſe prophets, a lying ſpirit to deceiue <hi>Achab:</hi> yet we may ſee, both the willingneſſe of Sathan to lie and deceiue: &amp; alſo how the falſe prophets did moſt wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſtubbornly mainteine their lying pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies. <hi>1. King. 22.21, 24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What ſaieſt thou to the example of Chriſt in this thing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this example we may ſee:</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:52"/>Firſt, how he gaue his ſon to death. <hi>Ioh. 3.16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, how Chriſt did moſt willingly giue himſelfe to death. <hi>Ioh. 10.15.</hi> &amp; <hi>13.12. Phil. 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, how <hi>Iudas</hi> his ſeruant betraied him for money. <hi>Matth. 26.48.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, how the Scribes, Prieſts, &amp; Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies moſt gladly gaue money, and reioyced therein. <hi>Luke. 22.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, how <hi>Pilate</hi> deliuered him to death for feare. <hi>Iohn. 19.12, 13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, how ſatan ſought the ſame, &amp; brought it to paſſe by his inſtruments. <hi>Iohn. 13.27, 30.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Make this example more plaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In it we may ſee the rich goodnes of God, and of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt: of God, in that hee ſpared not his onely Sonne: of Ieſus Chriſt, in that he was content in his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to pay the ranſome for the ſinnes of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but it was moſt wicked in the inſtruments, for they committed a horrible fact, in murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring an innocent man, and in putting to death the Sonne of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But, did they it not for the ſame ende that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13766:52"/>
God did; namely, for the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his people?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No verely: for as I ſaide before, <hi>Iudas</hi> did the ſame for money, the Scribes and Phariſies for enuie, <hi>Pilate</hi> for feare of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the Diuel to take away all hope of redemption and ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; alſo to bring the murtherers by his meanes into the wrath of God, and ſo vpon them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: therefore in either and euerie of them was it wicked and worthie of condemnation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What dooſt thou conclude vpon this thing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That GOD in all his actions is moſt iuſt and cleere from ſinne; and that the wicked are moſt vniuſt: although they doo nothing (indéed) but what God hath appointed them to doo, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe not to be excuſed therein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If all things muſt come to paſſe as God hath before appointed, is it not then in vaine to vſe counſell, labor, praier, or any other meanes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If they be called vain things, becauſe they can not procure things to fall out, otherwiſe than God hath appointed &amp; decreed; they are vain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede:
<pb facs="tcp:13766:53"/>
but otherwiſe they are not vaine things but good meanes, by which (as inſtruments) God bringeth his counſells, and purpoſes to paſſe: wherefore God doth command vs to vſe them; and thereby (after a ſort) we are ſaide to be helpers to bring his certaine and euerlaſting purpoſe to paſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As how?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus: as God hath certainlie appointed, &amp; vndoubtedly decreed, how things ſhould come to paſſe, the time when, and the place where: ſo reſeruing the end &amp; euent vnto his ſecret coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, (which we may not ſearch into) he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs meanes (and alſo reaſon to vſe them) to bring things to paſſe: which he hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs to vſe, leauing the iſſue, and that which is ſecret vnto him; wherefore not to doo them, is to tempt God; as too much to truſt in them, is to diſtruſt God: ſo that, both of them (not rightly performed) is great wickednes againſt God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What examples haue you for this in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Scriptures?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:13766:53"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Sauiour Chriſt, although he was hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie and tempted of Sathan, yet would he not depende vppon the meane, and vſe vnlawfull meanes to diſtruſt in God; neither yet when he was vpon the pinacle, being tempted of Satan to fall downe vnder the ſhewe of Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, yet would he not tempt God in neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the meanes to goe downe by the ſteps. <hi>Ma. 4.</hi> And of this you may ſée more in the booke of God, how <hi>Moſes, Dauid,</hi> and <hi>Paule,</hi> vſed the meanes of praier, labour, and all other honeſt &amp; lawfull things, to bring their matters to paſſe; although they knew that al things wer wroght and came to paſſe by Gods prouidence. <hi>Exod. 14.13, 14, 15. pſal. 3.5, 6, 8. 1. Sam. 19.11, 12. Actes 27.22, 23.24, 25, 30, 31.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the vſe of this doctrine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, faith in God. <hi>Pſal. 3.5, 6, 7, 8,</hi> &amp; <hi>23.</hi> the whole. <hi>pſal. 37.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, comfort. <hi>2. Kings. 6.16, 17. Acts. 27.24, 25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, patience in all our troubles; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God (who is our Father) ſendeth afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb facs="tcp:13766:54"/>
for our comfort, and will returne them to our good. <hi>Rom. 5.3, 4. pſalm. 37.7. Iam. 1.2, 3, 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, we ought to vſe all godly and honeſt meanes: as, <hi>Matth. 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, praier for them. <hi>Pſal. 50.14, 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, labour to attaine them in time of want by induſtries.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Phiſicke in ſickneſſe. <hi>Matth. 9.12. Eſay. 38.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, flight in perſecution. <hi>Matth. 10.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthlie, meate, drinke, and cloath, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our pilgrimage. <hi>Act. 27.33, 34, 35, 36. Matth. 14.15,</hi> to <hi>22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, we ought to tie God to them, neither to depende on them as things of of neceſſitie. <hi>Matth. 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>
               <hi>The end of the firſt</hi> part.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:13766:54"/>
            <head>The ſecond part of the Catechiſme.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LEt vs come vnto the ſecond part of our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme, and tell me, what is the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The redemption of mankinde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is redemption?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is our deliuerance in Ieſus Chriſt from al the former euils of our fall: as the power of ſinne, the curſe of God, and eternall death: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, a preparing (for vs) of an eſtate of happines, more excellent than the firſt. <hi>Galat. 3.13, 14. Gal. 1.4. Titu. 2.14. Rom. 8.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How is Chriſt our redeemer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, by the ordinance of GOD his father. <hi>Luke. 1. Acts. 4.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, by affinity, in taking vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him our nature, &amp; ſo to become our head &amp; elder brother.
<pb facs="tcp:13766:55"/>
               <hi>Eph. 5.30. Heb. 2.16, 17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, by right: as,</p>
            <p>Firſt, in that hee is Lorde of the whole world: for all things were made and are ruled by him. <hi>Iohn. 1.2, 3, 4, 5. Col. 1.16, 17. Heb. 1.2, 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe he hath redéemed his people by his obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, in ſhedding of his precious bloud. <hi>Rom. 5.6, 7, 8, 9. 1. pet. 1.18, 19, 20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What things belong vnto Chriſt our Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Three things?</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, perfect wiſe.</item>
               <item>Secondly, perfect rich.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, perfect ſtrong.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why perfect wiſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt to bring to naught the craftie deuiſes of Sathan and his complices. <hi>1. Cor. 1.19, 20, 24, 25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to make his people wiſe to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and to forſake al the ſubtilties of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13766:55"/>
and his inſtruments, in hereſies, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt manners. <hi>2. Tim. 3.15.16, 17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why perfect rich?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, to be of ſufficient abilitie to redéeme his people, and to pay the price of redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the which he hath moſt fully and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently alreadie done, by his death and bloud. <hi>Titus. 2.14. col. 1.11, 12, 13, 14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to make his people rich in faith, obedience, and all other heauenly &amp; ſpirituall graces. <hi>Ro. 1.8. 1. cor. 6.7. eph. 1.3. col. 1.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why of power?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, to ouercome his enemies, and the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of his people; as ſatan, ſinne, and eternall death. <hi>1. Cor. 15.54, 55, 56, 57. Heb. 2.14, 15. 1. Iohn 3.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to deliuer his people from theſe their enemies, and to giue them ſtrength to ouercome. <hi>Rom. 7.24, 25. 1. cor. 15. eph. 6.12.</hi> to <hi>18. 1. Iohn 5.4, 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is there anie other Sauior, than Chriſt onely?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:56"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: for hee it is that muſt both ſaue from death eternall, and giue life euerlaſting. <hi>Ioh. 3.16.</hi> and <hi>5.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What think you of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſeeke their ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> els where, as in their works, &amp; good inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, they herein denie Chriſt to be the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sauiour: for he will be a whole Sauiour or elſe none. <hi>Acts. 4.12. Matth. 3.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, they make themſelues to be half ſauiours, and to be equal &amp; copartners with Chriſt, in the work of redemtion. <hi>tit. 3.4, 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, they reſiſt the ordinance and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crée of God, who appointed Chriſt to bee the ſole Sauior of mankinde. <hi>Matt. 1.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, in ſtéed of heauen &amp; euerlaſting life, they (by their good intents and workes) doo purchaſe hell and euerlaſting death. <hi>Ioh. 3.17, 36.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What vſe ought we to make of this point?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, to note how miſerable we were of our ſelues after our fall: as,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:13766:56"/>Firſt, in ſinne. <hi>Pſal. 51.5. Ier. 17.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, vnder the wrath of God. <hi>eph. 2.3</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, captiues to the diuell. <hi>eph. 2.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, inheritors of hell, &amp; eternal death. <hi>Rom. 6.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the great and rich mercie of God,</p>
            <p>Firſt, in giuing vs a Sauiour, that might redeeme vs from ſinne, ſatan and hell. <hi>Eph. 2.4, 5. Tit. 3.4, 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in ſeeking to reconcile vs to him ſelfe, and to make vs his children, &amp; righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. <hi>2. cor. 5.18, 19, 20, 21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, in giuing vs thereby euerlaſting life, and eternall happineſſe. <hi>Ioh. 5.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seeing we are now redeemed in Chriſt: are we now therfore in a better and more happier eſtate vnder Chriſt our head, than <hi>Adam</hi> was in his innocencie in Paradice?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea ſurely, the eſtate of Gods children is now more excellent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe wee haue an excellent head, to
<pb facs="tcp:13766:57"/>
wit Chriſt, which <hi>Adam</hi> had not in the time of his innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie before his fal: <hi>Eph. 1.22. col. 1.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, God is more néerer ioyned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, than he was vnto <hi>Adam;</hi> (at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time) for he hath taken vpon himſelf ſince <hi>Adams</hi> fal, our humane nature, and ioyned the ſame to his diuine nature, and is become one with vs (ſinne excepted) <hi>Ephe. 5.30. Heb. 2.16. 1. Pet. 2.23. 1. Ioh. 3.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, our ſaluation is more certain, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was vnder <hi>Adam:</hi> for then we had no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to ſtand in the perfection of our creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but now in Chriſt it is moſt certaine and firme, becauſe it is grounded</p>
            <p>Firſt, vpon the euerlaſting &amp; vnchang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able decrée and purpoſe of God. <hi>Epheſ. 1. 11.2. Tim. 2.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, vppon the euerlaſting mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God in Chriſt. <hi>2. Tim. 1.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, vpon his faithfulneſſe, truth, and righteouſnes. <hi>1. cor. 1.9. 1. theſ. 5.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, vpon his inuincible power &amp; omnipotencie. <hi>Iohn 10.27, 28, 29.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, God doth not onely giue vs hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen (which <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould haue had in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie) but alſo maketh vs heirs (yea ioint
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13766:57"/>
heires) with Chriſt in glorie, the which <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould neuer haue had, if he had ſtoode in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie: ſo that wee maie ſee our eſtate farre better than <hi>Adams</hi> in Paradice. <hi>Rom. 8.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And is not man made more excellent, than the Angels in heauen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes verely: for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Chriſt tooke vpon him our nature, and exalted it aboue all principalities, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Dominions. <hi>Eph. 1.20, 21, 22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, man is made the Lord and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the whole world, &amp; that through grace in Chriſt: which rule and lorldlie authoritie, was neuer giuen vnto the Angels. <hi>Pſalm. 8.</hi> the whole.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Angels by the free mercies of God, are made the ſeruants of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to defend and comfort them: for they are the miniſtring ſpirits, ſent foorth to miniſter (for their ſakes that ſhall be heires to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) <hi>pſal. 34.7. Heb. 1.14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In that thou ſaiſt, that man is reſtored to a better eſtate than <hi>Adam</hi> in his firſt innocencie
<pb facs="tcp:13766:58"/>
in Paradice, &amp; is become more excellent than Angels: is thy meaning of all mankinde, &amp; of all perſons generally?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No ſurelie, but onely of the faithfull, who are grafted into the bodie of Chriſt by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt; as for infidels, hipocrites, heretikes, libertines, and atheiſts, their eſtate is no better than the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels in hell, in ſhame and confuſion for euer and euer. <hi>Reuel. 21.28. Eph. 5.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why; died not Chriſt for all men, as well as for a certaine number?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: Chriſt died not for all; for if Chriſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for all: then</p>
            <p>Firſt, there is no election. <hi>2. Tim. 3.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, God ſhould be then vniuſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne anie. <hi>Rom. 3, 4. pſal. 51.4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, al haue not faith. <hi>2. the .3.2. tit. 1.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the ſpirit of Chriſt belongeth one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the faithfull. <hi>Rom. 8.9, 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Was there anie imperfection in the ſacrifice of Chriſt, in that it was not ſufficient for all?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:13766:58"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was no imperfection in the ſacrifice of Chriſts bodie and ſoule, for he was perfect and holy: alſo it was ſufficient for all people, but ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual onely vnto thoſe, which lay hold on him through faith. <hi>he. 10.10, 12, 14.</hi> &amp; <hi>9.25, 26, 28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Scripture ſaith, God would haue al men come to the knoledge of the truth, &amp; be ſaued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word (all) muſt be conſidered after this manner: that</p>
            <p>Firſt, hee offereth grace vnto all, but all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not the ſame.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that word muſt bee vnderſtood, ſome of all Nations.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſome of all callings: as
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, Princes.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, ſubiects.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, parents.</item>
                  <item>Fourthly, children.</item>
                  <item>Fiftly, maſters.</item>
                  <item>Sixthly, ſeruants.</item>
                  <item>Seuenthly, men.</item>
                  <item>Eightly, women.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Some of all which, euen thoſe that lay hold
<pb facs="tcp:13766:59"/>
vpon Chriſt by a liuely &amp; true faith) ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and liue. <hi>1. Iohn. 5.10, 11, 12, 13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, we muſt conſider, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his reueled will is equally ruled by his ſecret wil, and that they be not contrarie the one to the other, although they ſeeme ſo to our fooliſh iudgements.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, that God is ſtable and vnchangeable in all his waies and workes. <hi>Iam. 1, 17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What moued God to ſaue ſome, &amp; damne other ſome? In that he ſaueth ſome, is it for that they deſerue the ſame; or did he foreſee, that they would both beleeue, and worke out their ſaluation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His owne mercie is the cauſe, that he ſaueth ſome out of the ſinfull lumpe of <hi>Adam:</hi> for</p>
            <p>Firſt, all deſerued damnation; for the beſt worke after regeneration, is defiled with ſin; and the reward of ſinne is death: how much more then deſerue we death before God doth regenerate vs by his ſpirit. <hi>1. cor. 13.9. Ro. 7.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, faith is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only gift of god. <hi>eph. 2.8</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, we cannot work wel, before God regenerate vs vnto good works. <hi>eph. 2.9.10</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:13766:59"/>Fourthly, in that he dampneth other ſome, it is of right, and according to his righteous iudgements: for that it is written: <hi>if you do this you ſhall liue, if you do not yee ſhall die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How ſhall we bee perſwaded of our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thorough faith. <hi>Gal. 3.11. Gal. 2.16. Rom. 3.27, 28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A firme perſwaſion grounded vpon a ſounde knowledge in ſacred Scriptures, that God is reconciled and become both our God and father, thorough the merits, obedience, and bloudſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Ieſus Chriſt; in whome wee ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and haue eternal life, ſo aſſuredly, as though wee poſſeſſed the ſame already: which faith is wrought by the holy Ghoſt in the hearts of the elect, thorough the miniſterie and preaching of the word. <hi>Rom. 5.1, 2. Rom. 8.38, 39.</hi> and <hi>3.24. Ephe. 3.17. Ephe. 1.13. 1. Ioh. 3.1, 2, 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then our faith muſt not bee wauering, but
<pb facs="tcp:13766:60"/>
firme in Chriſt and his promiſes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It muſt be firme and not wauering as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> teacheth: for note this; that not he (which doubteth ſhall be ſaued, but hee that beleeueth, and is rooted and grounded in the ſame faith. <hi>Col. 1.23.</hi> and <hi>2.7. Iohn. 3.16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where ſhall we finde this our redeemer and redemption deliuered vnto vs more fullie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond parte of the articles of our faith, which are ſixe in number.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Into how many partes may they be diuided?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two: that is, <list>
                  <item>Firſt, of the baſe eſtate of Chriſts birth, and his humilitie in ſuffring: which the three firſt articles ſheweth.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, of his exaltation and excellencie in all perfection and glorie in the other three articles.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <trailer>
               <hi>The ende of the first parte <hi>of the Creede.</hi>
               </hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:13766:60"/>
            <head>¶The ſecond parte of the Creede.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>REherſe the firſt article of the ſecond parte of Creede?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And in Ieſus Chriſt his onely Sonne our Lord, which was conceiued by the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of how many partes dooth it conſiſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of fourth: That is, <list>
                  <item>Firſt, Ieſus.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, onely ſonne.</item>
                  <item>Fourthly, Lord.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What dooth this word <hi>(Ieſus)</hi> ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sauiour. <hi>Math. 1.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whome dooth he ſaue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His people. <hi>Matth. 1.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:61"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How dooth he ſaue them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the ſacrifice of himſelf. <hi>Heb. 10.10, 29, 20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the propiciatorie ſacrifice?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ieſus Chriſt is the propiciatorie ſacrifice, for he, as the onely good high prieſt, did once giue himſelfe for his, that repent and beleeue; that the wrath of God his father might be appeaſed, and that his people might be both ſanctified, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in him euermore. <hi>Heb. 7.26, 27. 1. Theſ. 1.10. 2. Cor. 5.20, 21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who are his people?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All thoſe that haue his ſpirite, and doo beleeue in him. <hi>Iohn. 1.12, 13. Romans. 8.9. Iohn. 10.26.27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>From what hath he ſaued them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From ſinne, ſathan, death, and hell. <hi>Titu. 2.14. Heb. 2.14. 1. Iohn. 3.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:13766:61"/>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why? The very elect doo ſinne continuallie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea: but ſinne ſhall not raigne ouer them, much leſſe, damne them. <hi>Roma. 6.3, 4, 5, 6, 11, 12, 13, 14. 1. Ioh. 3.5, 6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo wee ſee how ſathan dooth afflict the godlie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although ſathan, by the permiſſion and will of God, dooth afflict the godlie, both to try their faith, and exerciſe their patience: yet he cannot hold them in captiuitie to deuoure them. <hi>Ephe. 4.8. Heb. 2.14, 15. Matth. 16.18. 1. Ioh. 3.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alſo the godlie doo die continuallie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although they die; yet death is made to them, the gate of immortallitie; and they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from eternall death: for which cauſe, Chriſt eſpeciallie died. <hi>Heb. 9.27, 28. Iohn. 5.24. 2. Cor. 5.1,</hi> to <hi>12. 1 Theſ. 4.15,</hi> to the end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The elect people are alſo troubled in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience with the torments of hell oftentimes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:62"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thoſe torments are not their eternal por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a time they ſuffer, that therby they may know both Chriſt: &amp; themſelues. <hi>Pſa. 34.18, 20. Eſa. 54.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. 1. Cor. 10.13. Heb. 12.5.</hi> to <hi>24. Reu. 3.19.20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why is he called Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe he was anoynted of his father. <hi>Pſal. 49.6, 7. Heb. 1.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What was his annointment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fulnes of his Godhead. <hi>Col. 1.19.</hi> and <hi>2.3.9. Iohn. 3.34.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What parte was anointed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not his deuine: but humaine nature. <hi>Iohn. 3, 34. Heb. 1.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why was he anointed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be our prophet, prieſt, &amp; king. <hi>Re. 19.16. Pſa. 2.6. De. 18.15. Act. 37. Pſa. 110. He. 55.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:13766:62"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How is he our Prophet?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in that he ſpake by his ſpirit in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. <hi>1. Pet. 1.10, 11, 12. 2. Pet. 1.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in that he hath fulfilled all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, and promiſes, that were foreſhewed of him. <hi>2. Cor. 1.20. Matth. 5.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe he hath reuealed the wil of his father vnto vs. <hi>Iohn. 18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How is he our prieſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in that he offered a ſacrifice for vs his people. <hi>Heb. 9.25, 25,</hi> and <hi>10.10.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in that hee doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually teach vs his people by his word and ſpirit <hi>Ioh. 15.26. Iohn. 14.26.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, in that he maketh continuall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto his father for vs. <hi>ro. 2.34. he. 7.25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How a King?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quered, ſin, ſatan, death, &amp; hel. <hi>1. cor. 15.54.</hi> to <hi>57. he. 2.14.15. 1. Iho. 3.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he maketh his ſubiects co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors
<pb facs="tcp:13766:63"/>
ouer ſinne, ſathan, death and hell. <hi>Col. 1.12, 13. 1. Cor. 15.54.</hi> to <hi>57.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, in that hee ruleth and gouerneth his people by his lawes. <hi>Pſalm. 2.10, 11, 12. Ioh. 10.27, 28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, in that he will giue his people a ſpirituall, and eternall kingdome. <hi>1. Pet. 5.10, 11. Reuel. 1.5. Reuel. 22.1, 2, 3, 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How is he the onely ſonne of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By nature, of the ſubſtance of his father from euerlaſting. <hi>Iohn. 1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why? We are the ſonnes of God alſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true: but it is by adoption thorough the grace of God in Chriſt. <hi>Rom. 8.15, 16. Ga. 4.4, 5, 6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is adoption?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This: that God adopteth vnto himſelfe his elect (not for that he had not another ſonne, (for he had his only begotten ſonne Chriſt, in whom he was well pleaſed) but for that, in all the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13766:63"/>
of man, he had yet no children: for in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> wee were all become the children of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, and the veſſels of Gods wrath: wherefore God ſent his naturall and legittimate Sonne Chriſt into the World, that thorough his rich grace; hee might adopte vnto himſelfe many children out of our kinde. <hi>Matth. 3.17. Rom. 8.15, 16. Gal. 4.4, 5, 6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The free fauour of God, not only pardoning the ſinnes of his elect children, but alſo in clad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them with innocencie and righteouſnes of Chriſt, to their euerlaſting iuſtifications. <hi>Rom. 3.24. 1. Cor. 5.2. Titu. 2.11.14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What gather you by this word (Lord?)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt how Chriſt hath brought his people with a precious price, that is, with his death and bloud. <hi>1. Cor. 6.20.</hi> and <hi>7.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, how he will deliuer and defende his people, from the power of ſinne, ſathan, eternall death and hell. <hi>Matth. 16.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, how his people muſt yeeld obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:13766:64"/>
to him and his lawes. <hi>Act. 3.23. 1. pe. 5.14, 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, how he is God and Lord of the whole world. <hi>Iohn. 1.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the third article: <hi>which was conceaued by the holy Ghoſt, borne of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mary?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that hee is verie man of the fleſh of the Virgin his mother. <hi>Matth. 1.21, 22. Luke. 1.31, 32. Rom. 4.3, 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that his birth, was pure and frée from all infection of ſinne, and the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of nature, in that he was not conceiued af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the common manner of men, but by the power and mightie operation of the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Luke. 1.35. Iohn. 17.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that hee was conceiued in the wombe of the virgin by the holy Ghoſt, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe he might be:</p>
            <p>Firſt, an vndefiled prieſt. <hi>Heb. 7.26, 27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, a pure ſacrifice for the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his people. <hi>Heb. 10.10. 1. Pet. 1.19.20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:13766:64"/>Thirdly, that he might ſanctifie his people in all holines. <hi>Iohn. 17.19. 1. Pet. 2.22. &amp;c. 1. Iohn. 3.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the veritie of Gods Propheſies is thereby to be ſeene.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in reſpect of the perſons of <hi>Marie</hi> and Chriſte. <hi>Iſay. 7.14. Matth. 1.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time when the ſcepter ſhould departe from <hi>Iuda. Gene. 49.10. Mat. 2.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, of the place in <hi>Bethelem. Micah. 5.2. Math. 2.6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you out of the fourth article <hi>he ſuffred vnder Pontius Pilate, was crucified, dead and buried, he deſcended into hell?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, vnder whome he was iudged to death <hi>(vz.)</hi> vnder that feareful and falſe iudge <hi>Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Pilate,</hi> to deliuer vs, from that feareful, iuſt, and eternall iudgement of God his father. <hi>Mat. 26.</hi> and <hi>27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the great ſufferings that Chriſt ſuffred both in body &amp; ſoule: namely, in body he was crucified, killed, dead and buried: and in his ſoule and bodie, (in the garden and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the croſſe,) he ſuffred the torments of hel.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:65"/>
               <hi>Matth. 26.46. Heb, 9.25.26. 1. Pet. 3.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the endes, why hee ſuffered theſe things? That was: to make a ſufficient ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and a ful ſatiſfaction for al our ſinnes, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to auoide the horrible puniſhment due vnto vs. <hi>1. Pet. 3.18. Gal. 3.13, 14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, to fulfill all propheſies and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, ſacrifices and figures, of his death and our ſaluation. <hi>Gen. 3.15. Eſay. 33.</hi> the whole, <hi>Iohn. 19.30.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now let vs come vnto the ſecond point, of Chriſts exhaltation in glorie and excellencie in perfection. What learne you in the ſixt article, <hi>the third day he roſe againe from the dead?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that Chriſt did riſe out of the graue, with the ſame body, on the third day, according to his owne Propheſies, and the figure of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas. Matth. 12.39.</hi> and <hi>16.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, by the power of his reſurrection he ſheweth vnto vs, that hee hath ouercome the power of the diuell, ſinne, death, and hell. <hi>Mat. 18.4, 5. 1. Pet. 3.21, 22. Heb. 2.14, 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that hee hath purchaſed for vs, righteouſnes vnto iuſtification to eternall
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13766:65"/>
life. <hi>Rom. 4.25. 1. Pet. 1.3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, by the vertue of his death, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſinne to die in vs, and by the vertue of his reſurrection, hee cauſeth vs to riſe vnto newnes of life, <hi>Rom. 6.4, 5. 1. Pet. 4.1, 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, his riſing is an aſſured pledge, that our bodies ſhall riſe againe to immortalitie. <hi>1. Cor. 15.12, 16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the imputation of righteouſnes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is an accounting of Chriſts righteouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to bee our owne thorough faith, whereby we are preſented both iuſt and blameles, before God (both his and our father.) <hi>Phil. 3.9, 10. 2. Cor. 5.27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the ſixth article, <hi>he aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into Heauen and ſitteth at the right hand of God?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt that he is aſcended into Heauen, from out of this earth in his manhoode, according to the Propheſies of his aſſention. <hi>Pſalm. 65.19. Acts. 1.9, 10, 11. Ephe. 4.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, his aſcenſion is a pledge, that
<pb facs="tcp:13766:66"/>
we ſhall likewiſe aſcende after him: for he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſended to prepare a place of glorie for his people. <hi>Iohn. 14.3. Ephe. 2.6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, he is aſcended to make interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for vs to God his father. <hi>Rom. 8.38. He. 7.24, 25, 26, 27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, that all power is giuen vnto him and how he is of equall authoritie with God his father. <hi>Matth. 8.18. Ephe. 1.20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, to enrich his Church, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende her againſt the gates of hell. <hi>Ephe. 4.7, 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to puniſh the wicked to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. <hi>1. Cor. 15.24.</hi> to <hi>29.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the ſeauenth article, <hi>from thence hee ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the dead?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that there is a day appointed for the iudgement of the quicke and dead, according to the Prophecies of the worde of God: but when this ioyfull and fearefull day ſhall be; the verie Angels doo not knowe neither yet the ſonne of man. <hi>Actes. 17.31. Marke. 13.32. Iohn. 5.27, 28, 29.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:13766:66"/>Secondly, who is the iudge, that muſt iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the godly, and iudge the wicked: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Actes. 10.42. 2. Corinth. 5.10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, it miniſtreth to the godlie,</p>
            <p>Firſt this comfort; that their ſauiour and elder brother, is their iudge to iuſtifie them, and at that day ſhall deliuer them, from all ſinne, feare of death, hell and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, and all other miſeries. <hi>Rom. a8.33.34. Luke. 21.28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that (to the great terror of the godleſſe, who feare not God, nor loue either Chriſt, or his Goſpell) he ſhall bee their iudge to their fearefull and iuſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. <hi>2. Theſ. 1.6, 7, 8, 9. Reuel. 6.12.</hi> to <hi>17.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>
               <hi>The end of the ſecond <hi>part.</hi>
               </hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:13766:67"/>
            <head>¶ The third parte of the Catechiſme.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>NOw let vs come vnto the third parte of our Catechiſme, and ſhewe mee what is the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our ſanctification.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is ſanctification?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a ſetting free at libertie, from the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of ſinne, vnto the freedome of righteouſenes, that therein his people might walke continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, receiuing from Chriſt their daily ſtrength. <hi>Iohn. 8. Rom. 6. Phil. 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where ſhall wee finde the ſame deliuered at large vnto vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third parte of the articles of our faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Into how many partes ſhall wee diuide this point?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:13766:67"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Into three: as; <list>
                  <item>Firſt, who ſanctifieth (that is) the Holie Ghoſt, as in the <hi>8.</hi> article appeareth.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, whom he ſanctifieth, (vz.) his Church: and the meanes whereby he ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth it, as in the <hi>9.</hi> article.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly of the ſpiritual benefites and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that belongeth to the Church onely, in the <hi>10, 11,</hi> and <hi>12,</hi> articles.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which is the firſt Article of the 3. part of the Articles of our faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This: <hi>I beleeue in the holy Ghoſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you out of the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt that the holie Ghoſt is God, proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Father and the Sonne, the thirde perſon in Trinitie, and nothing inferiour to the Father nor the Sonne, either in ſubſtaunce or glorie, but of the ſame ſubſtance and glory with them. <hi>Matth. 28.19. Acts. 5.3, 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it is he that inſtructeth, ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, comforteth, and confirmeth the elect, in
<pb facs="tcp:13766:68"/>
the trueth of the promiſes of the Goſpell of Chriſt vnto ſaluation, and euerlaſting life. <hi>Eph. 1.13. Tit. 3.4, 5, 6. 2. cor. 1.21, 22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the holy Ghoſt executeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great prouidence of God, ouer all his creatures, whereby they continue in their eſtate, &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth the euent and ſucceſſe of things, that nothing commeth to paſſe by chance, or any way els, but by his diſpoſition &amp; apointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <hi>Gene. 1.2. Pſal. 145.7,</hi> to <hi>11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, that the ſinne againſt the holie Ghoſt, ſhal not be forgiuen in this life, nor in the life to come. <hi>Matth. 12.31, 32. Heb. 6.4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whom doth the holie Ghoſt ſanctifie, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and confirme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the people of God in Chriſt: who are called the Church of God, &amp; ſpouſe of Chriſt. <hi>Ephe. 5.26, 27. 1. cor. 1.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rehearſe the Article.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I beleeue that there is a catholique Church, &amp; a communion of Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:13766:68"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the Church of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is all the elect of what ſexe and eſtate ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, which haue been, are, and ſhall be, vnto the endes of the world; which are called by the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly working of the holie Ghoſt; by externall mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie and preaching of the word, confirmed by ſacraments, and finally gouerned by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie diſcipline of their head Chriſt. <hi>Iohn. 20.16.</hi> &amp; <hi>17.20. Col. 3.10, 11. Gal. 3.26, 27, 28, 29. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe. 4.30. Rom. 10.17. Rom. 4.11. Math. 18.15,</hi> to <hi>21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſaiſt, that the church conſiſteth of the elect: therefore tell me, what is election?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the euerlaſting and vnchangeable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, of the almightie, wiſe, and iuſt God; who of his free and rich mercie, through faith in the bloud of his onelie beloued Sonne, hath choſen to life eternall, ſuch as it pleaſed himſelfe. <hi>Eph. 1.2. Tim. 1.9. 1. Pet. 1.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you out of this article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:69"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that there is an election belonging vnto all eſtates, and that through Gods mercie, and Chriſts merites apprehended by faith. <hi>Rom. 9.24, 25, 26, 27. Eph. 1.4, 5, 6, 7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is a Church of Chriſt, (partly militarie, and partly triumphant) the which Church ſhall bee to the ende of the world, and (in the life to come) ſhall be euer more without ende, let the diuell, and men rage, and roare while they will. <hi>Reuel. 6.5.6, 7. 2. Tim. 1.9, 10, 19, 20, 21, 22. Matth. 16.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, As their election is of God, and their redemption in Chriſt: ſo their vocation and ſanctification is of the holy Ghoſt, by the miniſterie, and preaching of the word and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. <hi>1. cor. 6.10. Rom. 10.17. Gal. 3.2. Tit. 3.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, he gouerneth the flock of Chriſt by his effectuall working in their hearts, and his word. <hi>1. Cor. 1.2, 3, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, that there muſt be an holy fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and a godly Communion of the ſaints of God, in all holines and righteouſnes. <hi>pſa. 85.10. Heb. 12.14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:13766:69"/>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As in the beginning of this Article, thou didſt ſet downe the doctrine of election: and how onely it dooth belong to the faithfull me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof, ſo tell me more plainlie thy mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will: and that is this; although the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full are but few in number, yet the greater part of them, doo conſiſt of the poore, of the fooles, &amp; of the weake ones of the worlde, to whome (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be ſo accounted of among men) the election, through grace, doth belong onely vnto them. <hi>1. cor. 1.27,</hi> to the end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If there be an election, there is alſo a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is moſt true: there is alſo a reprobation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is reprobation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is an vtter reiecting and hardening of the hearts of thoſe, who are ordeined to euerlaſting deſtruction, that they cannot repent, &amp; beleeue the Goſpell to ſaluation. <hi>Roman 9.17, 18, 22.
<pb facs="tcp:13766:70"/>
Iud. 3. Reuel. 17.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How are the wicked in fault, if God appoint the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to deſtruction; for who can reſiſt his will?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwere you thus: that</p>
            <p>Firſt, the counſell of God excuſeth not the wickednes of the wicked: for the reprobate committeth ſinne moſt willingly, &amp; without conſtraint on the Lords behalfe; ſo that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his reprobation bee of the Lord, his damnation is of himſelf, as <hi>Pharoah, Iudas. Exod. 9, 10,</hi> and <hi>11.</hi> chap. <hi>Matth. 26.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the Apoſtle teacheth vs to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelues, and not to carpe at the déepe ſecrets of God, when he ſaith: <hi>Who art thou ô man, that thou ſhouldeſt plead with God. <hi>Ro. 9.20, 21.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But if it be ſo, (touching the life to come) that God hath appointed alreadie the elect and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, and hath appointed all the meanes to bring his counſell to paſſe; we may do what we liſt: for if appointed to be ſaued, we ſhall bee ſaued; if appointed to be damned, we ſhall be damned: and therefore all labour loſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:13766:70"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is certeine that we cannot fruſtrate &amp; alter the counſel of God: no, not the leaſt mean there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto belonging: for then there ſhould be in God <list>
                  <item>(Firſt, darkneſſe.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, ignorance.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, weakneſſe)</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>If things coulde fall out otherwiſe, than God ſaw ſhould come to paſſe, and as he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had appointed. <hi>Iam. 1.17. 2. Timoth. 2.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is it not then in vaine, as I haue alreadie ſaid, to labor, and to vſe the meanes to enioy life, &amp; to doo the workes commanded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: for God hath appointed the meanes how to come to ſaluation in his foreknowledge, and vnchangable purpoſe, namely, the preaching of the word, reading and meditating thereof; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, the ſacraments, &amp; praier: theſe things muſt be vſed, and thoſe that are the ſheepe of Chriſt, ſhall, and wil vſe them. And as for good works, we are both commanded to do them, &amp; to make our election ſure by them. <hi>Ioh. 10.26, 27. 2. pet. 1.8, 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:71"/>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why dooth God ſaue ſome, and damne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that he might ſhew his mercie to his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to the praiſe of his glorie. <hi>Rom. 9.15, 23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that he might ſhewe foorth his iuſtice vpon the reprobate, to the praiſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to be glorified to their condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Rom. 9.22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What fruits haue we of this doctrine of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, it miniſtreth great ſtrength vnto our faith, againſt all temptation. <hi>1. cor. 10.13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, comfort in all our afflictions, becauſe we ſhall not bee ouercome by them, nor periſh in them. <hi>Rom. 8.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, thankſgiuing is thereby requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>Ephe. 1.8. Rom. 15.9, 10, 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, for his vnchangeable truth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, his euerlaſting mercies.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, his inuincible power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then you firmely beleeue, that it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13766:71"/>
for the elect of God to fall away?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea verely: for although it were poſſible, that heauen, earth, men, and angells, ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire againſt them; yet they cannot be loſt; no, not the leaſt, nor the pooreſt of them: for God is both vnchaungeable in his purpoſe, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightineſſe it ſelfe: therefore his counſell ſhall ſtande for euer, (and that for his) againſt the gates of hell, <hi>Rom. 8.38, 39. Matth. 16.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But we ſee manie (after they haue profeſſed the truth) haue fallen from the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true: but they neuer beléeued and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the truth in ſincerity of hart: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſpirit of God caſteth them out of the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the ſacred flocke of God, as hypocrites to their ſhame: for if they had bin of God (althogh ſubiect to many infirmities) they ſhuld not haue periſhed; for God would haue put his hand vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, and raiſed them vp, and kept them to euerlaſting life. <hi>Pſal. 145.14. 1. Ioh. 2.27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What are the meanes whereby he ſanctifieth his people?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:72"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt the miniſterie of the word. <hi>Iho. 17.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Sacraments. <hi>Titus. 3.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, diſcipline. <hi>Matth. 18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Praier. <hi>Matth. 7.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How dooth hee ſanctifie his Church by his word?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in that he begetteth and connecteth his people by the word. <hi>Pſal. 19.7. 1. Pet. 3.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in that hee worketh faith in the hearts of his people, and ſo purifieth their hearts by faith. <hi>Rom. 10.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, by the word (which is the two ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſworde) hee (with the one ſide) killeth the reprobate: and (with the other) cutteth off all the exile affections of his people, and reneweth them dailie to holines. <hi>Hebru. 4.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you hereby?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the excellencie and power of the word of God. <hi>2. Cor. 4.3.4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the neceſſitie of the word: for,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:13766:72"/>
where Propheſie wanteth, there the people periſh. <hi>Pro. 29.18. Hoſea. 4.6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the happines of them (that haue the worde preached for ſaluation) is both brought and offered vnto them. <hi>Titu. 2.11. 2. Cor. 6.1, 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, as there muſt needes bee blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ignorance, infidelitie, and al corruption, both of religion and manners: ſo the miſerie of them that haue not the word preached is here ſet downe. <hi>Iere. 88. Rom. 1.21. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let vs come to Sacraments, and tell mee, what is a Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sacrament is a viſible and earthly ſigne, repreſenting, inuiſible, &amp; ſupernaturall graces, not to bee ſeene by the carnall and outward eye of man, but with the eye of faith. Alſo a Seale to confirme our faith in the couenant of grace: and finallie a badge and marke of Chriſtianitie. <hi>Gene. 17.11. Rom. 4.11. Marke. 1.4, 8. Gala. 3.27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How many Sacraments are there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:73"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not ſeuen, as the Papiſts haue dreamed: but two, that is, Baptiſme, and the Lordes ſupper. <hi>1. cor. 10.16, 21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who is the author of theſe two ſacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Almightie God ordeined Baptiſme fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and Ieſus Chriſt the holy Supper vppon earth. <hi>Ioh. 1.32, 33. Matth. 26.26, 27, 28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hath man power to make ſacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: For, firſt they are part of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. <hi>Matt. 28.19, 20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, they witneſſe the goodneſſe of God vnto vs. <hi>Matth. 26.26, 27, 28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, they are ſeales to confirme our faith in the couenant of God in Chriſt. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. 4 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the word of ſaluation and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation muſt go with the ſignes, or els they are no ſacraments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What thinke you of them, that take vppon them to make Sacraments?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:13766:73"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their folly and preſumption is great: and herein they blaſpheme God, as though he knew not what was nceſſarie for his Church, without their raſhnes and diuelliſh pride. Beſides, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Moſes, Salomon,</hi> nor <hi>Paule,</hi> euer durſt to doo the ſame in any of Gods ſeruices. <hi>Exo. 35, 36, 37, 38.</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>25.4. 1. Reg. 6, 7, 8. 1. Cor. 11. Act. 7.44.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a ſacrament ordeined of God, of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique waſhing with water, once, in the name of the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy ghoſt: ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying thereby our remiſſion of ſinnes, morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and ſanctification in the death and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt. <hi>Iohn 1.33. Math. 28.19. Mark. 1.4, 8. Rom. 6.4, 5, 6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How many things haue we to conſider of in this Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the inſtitution of God. <hi>Ioh. 1.33.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, the external thing, water. <hi>mar. 1.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the promiſe: to wit, remiſſion of
<pb facs="tcp:13766:74"/>
ſinnes in Chriſt. <hi>Mark. 1.4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, faith in the promiſed ſéed, which is Chriſt. <hi>Marke. 16.16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doo you gather by Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that I am a vile ſinner, and the child of wrath by nature. <hi>Pſal. 51.5. Gene. 6.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, a profeſſion of my faith in the holie Trinitie, and of my ſaluation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes in the bloud of Chriſt. <hi>Mat. 28.19. Acts. 2.38.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the promiſe that God made to mee, to bee my God: and that I made vnto GOD, to denie the world, mortefie the olde man, reſiſt ſathan; and to delight in true righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes and holines, as it becommeth his obedient child who is renewed. <hi>Acts. 2.38, 39.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is the ſeale of righteouſnes and ſaluation vnto me, through the mercies of God in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Rom. 4.11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, the benefits which God offreth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee by Baptiſme, as the inſtrument by which I am ingrafted into Chriſts bodie. <hi>1. Cor. 12. Gal. 3.27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:13766:74"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the olde man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Al the corruption of our defiled nature, which we got by the Apoſtacie of our firſt parents <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and <hi>Eue:</hi> and all the cuſtome of ſinning, according to the conuerſation of olde. <hi>Ephe. 4.22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is Apoſtacie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is an vtter and whole intire falling away from the eſtate and perfection wherein we were firſt created: or now from the faith of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is mortification?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A continuall killing and ſubduing of the olde man. <hi>Col. 3.5. Gal. 5.27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is renewing or regeneration?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A begetting or newe birth in Chriſt, which is called the new man. <hi>Ephe. 4.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the new man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:75"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A renewing in the ſpirit by the Holie ghoſt, into true righteouſnes and holineſſe. <hi>Eph. 4.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What are the benefites receiued?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt remiſſion of ſinnes. <hi>Acts. 2.38.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the power of ſinne killed in me. <hi>Rom. 6.3, 4,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Holy ghoſt giuen vnto mee. <hi>Rom. 8.9. Tit: 3.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Faith confirmed in me. <hi>Rom. 4.11. Acts. 8.37, 38.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Can the outward ſigne, that is, water; giue the inuiſible graces, which are, remiſsion of ſinnes, regeneration, faith, and the Holy ghoſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, how can earthly things giue ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall graces: and how can the creature giue the things of the creator. <hi>Heb. 9.14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, remiſſion of ſins is only in the bloud of Chriſt through faith. <hi>Ephe. 1.7. col. 1.14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is the Holie ghoſt that muſt
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13766:75"/>
kill ſinne, and quicken vs vnto righteouſnes. <hi>Titu: 3.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, faith is the gift of God. <hi>Ephe. 2.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, the holy Ghoſt giueth himſelfe to his children. <hi>Rom. 8. Ephe. 1.13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If ſinnes be not waſhed away by Baptiſme; Why did <hi>Ananias</hi> ſay to <hi>Paul, Acts. 9, 17.</hi> that he ſhould waſh away his ſinne by Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> is put in minde (euen as all true and faithfull Chriſtians are) by the ſigne of Baptiſme, that his ſinnes were forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea: but the ſame Apoſtle ſaith. <hi>Ephe. 5.26.</hi> that the water in Baptiſme cleanſeth the Church and ſanctifieth her?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle (in the words going before, and in the words following after) ſheweth: that it is onely Chriſt, that dooth by his death and word, both cleanſe, and ſanctifie his Church: of which, Baptiſme is both a ſeale and figure.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:76"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Regeneration is attributed to the water in Baptiſme by the Apoſtle, in the third of <hi>Titus</hi> the fifth verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in that place: ſheweth, that rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration is onely the worke of the holy Ghoſt, and of no other; of which, the ſacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is a ſure figure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What if children die without Baptiſme: are they damned?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſaluation hangeth vppon election. <hi>Ephe. 1.4, 5, 6. 2. Timo. 1.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, God hath promiſed hée will bee a God to the faithfull and their ſeede. <hi>Gene. 17.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the kingdome of God belongeth to little children. <hi>Matth. 18.10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, onely ſaluation is in Chriſt, and without him no ſaluation. <hi>Acts. 12.4. Iohn. 3.16, 17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Verelie, verelie, J
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13766:76"/>
ſay vnto thee, except a man be borne of water and of the ſpirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdome of God.</hi> So that hee maketh it a neceſsitie, to bee baptiſed to ſaluation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, this place dooth nothing belong to the Sacrament of Baptiſme: for onely in that place our Sauiour Chriſt ſheweth, that <hi>Nicodemus</hi> could not be a fit inſtrument to receiue the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, without he were renewed by the ſpirit vnto righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>Secondly we cannot reade in this chapter, that <hi>Nicodemus</hi> was baptiſed, the which (if it had been of ſuch a neceſſitie) both he ſhould and would haue béen preſently baptiſed, and the Euangeliſt would haue noted the ſame.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, admit that Chriſt did ſpeake of Baptiſme, yet the worde muſt not bee ſo vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that he includeth ſaluation in water, but hee rather ioyneth water with the ſpirit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee teſtifieth and ſealeth vnto vs, (by that viſible ſigne) newnes of life, which God alone, doth work in vs by his holy ſpirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What gather you by this doctrine, of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:77"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, they are moſt cruell againſt poore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants.</p>
            <p>Secondly, moſt wicked to tie God to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall meanes and denie his couenant.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if all be damned that are not Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed; then all are ſaued, if they be Baptiſed.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, by this doctrine; although Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet if children die before they eat the fleſh and drinke the bloud of Chriſt they are dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <hi>Iohn. 6.53.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>May priuate men and women miniſter the Sacrament of Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No ſurely: for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Lord hath tied the ſame vnto his lawfull miniſters, with the preaching of the word. <hi>Matth. 28.19, 20. 1. Cor. 14.34, 35.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, if they may adminiſter Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, they may as well adminiſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lordes ſupper, and preach the word publiquelie; which things are abſurde and wicked.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>God was pleaſed with <hi>Zipporah</hi> her acte,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:13766:77"/>
in circumciſing her ſonne with a ſtone?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Almightie God, did not approue her facte; otherwiſe we might ſay, that the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping which the Gentiles (that were brought from <hi>Aſſiria</hi>) raiſed vp, did pleaſe God, becauſe the beaſts did ceaſe to afflict the people. <hi>Exod. 4.24, 25, 26. 2. Reg. 17.41.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that which is particuler, ought not to be made a generall example.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doo wee not ſinne moſt heynouſlie, if wee walke not according to our promiſe made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God in Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes verelie: for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, we breake our promiſe with GOD, and falſefie our faith with the holy Trinitie. <hi>Matth. 28.19. Titu. 3.4, 5, 6, 7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, wee crucifie a newe our ſauiour Chriſt, and tread the bloud of the holy coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant vnder foote. <hi>Heb. 6.6.</hi> and <hi>10.26, 27, 28, 29.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, wee grieue the holy Ghoſt, by whome the elect are ſealed vnto the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting redemption. <hi>Ephe. 4.29, 30.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:78"/>Fourthly, wee mock and grieue the holy Angels who reioyce at the repentance of a ſinner, and cauſe them to bee our enemies to deſtruction, who are appointed of God to be the miniſters of the elect vnto Saluation. <hi>Matth. 18.10. Luke. 15.10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, we giue offence vnto the Church: but <hi>it had been better that a Milstone had been hanged about our necks, and wee caſt into the Sea. <hi>Matth. 8.6, 7.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, wee doo not only bereaue our ſelues of all the ſpirituall gifts of Gods ſpirit: but alſo we are murtherers of our owne ſoules, in that we bereaue our ſelues of Chriſt, who is the very life it ſelfe. <hi>Iohn. 14.6. Roma. 8.9, 10, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſigne may not be neglected of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, may it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No, God forbid it ſhould: for if wee neglect and contemne the Sacrament, it is an accurſed and wicked kind of dealing in men; as namelie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Anabaptiſts who deny the Sacrament of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme to youg infants, wherein they ſhew their ignorance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:13766:78"/>For firſt they bee vnder the couenant, <hi>Exod. 4.24, 25, 26. Gene. 17.9, 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the kingdome of God belongeth vnto them. <hi>Matth. 18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now let vs come vnto the Lords ſupper: when did he inſtitute the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preſently, after the eating of the paſſeouer and alſo a little before his death: thereby</p>
            <p>Firſt, to ſhewe vnto vs, that the Paſſeouer was ended in him. <hi>1. Cor. 5.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to put vs alwaies in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his ſuffrings. <hi>Matth. 26.26, 27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the Lords ſupper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a holy banquet, and a ſacrament of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique eating and drinking of Bread and Wine: to put in minde all beleeuing Chriſtians (which are of a good and a ſound diſcretion) how Chriſt was put to death, and did ſhed his bloud, for the remiſſion of their ſinnes, and ſo is become their meate and drinke, (thorough faith) to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life. <hi>Mat. 29.26, 27. 1. Cor. 10.16. 1. Cor. 11.23, 24, 25.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:79"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How many things are to bee conſidered of, in this ſacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fouer: as firſt, Chriſt and his inſtitution. <hi>Math. 26.26. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the externall ſignes, Bread and Wine. <hi>Math. 26.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the promiſe of redemption, and remiſſion of ſinnes in Chriſt. <hi>1. Corinth. 11.23. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, faith in the promiſe to iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and euerlaſting life. <hi>Iohn. 66.54. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How is our faith nouriſhed and confirmed by the Lords ſupper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in that our ſauiour Chriſt giueth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto vs, therein aſſuring that his bodie was giuen vnto the death of the Croſſe, and his bloud ſhed for vs. <hi>Matth. 26.26, 27, 28. phil. 2.8. 1. pet. 2.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the bread and wine which wee take, and eate and drinke, (according to his holy inſtitution,) doo teach vs, that by faith we doo eate and drinke the body and bloud of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:13766:79"/>
Ieſus Chriſt, as the onely comfort and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of our ſoules. <hi>Iohn. 6.48, 51.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the Analogie betweene the ſignes, and the things ſignified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſtandeth, in feeding, nouriſhing, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, refreſhing: in vnion, and in fellowſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As how? Shew me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, as the bread and wine, doo feede, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and refreſh the naturall bodie of man; euen ſo, the bodie and bloud of our Lord and Sauior Chriſt (with the merits of his paſſion) doo ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuallie, feede, nouriſh, comfort, and refreſh, our poore famiſhed and thirſtie ſoules. <hi>Ioh. 6.32, 33.35. 1. Cor. 11.24, 25, 26.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, as many cornes and grapes are vnited into one loafe, and one wine: euen ſo, are wee vnited into one myſticall bodie, and haue vnion and fellowſhip with Chriſt; and bee as members one with another. <hi>1. Corin. 10.16, 17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then we do not, reallie, and verelie, eat and
<pb facs="tcp:13766:80"/>
drinke the naturall fleſh and bloud of Chriſt in the holy ſupper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: for, firſt it fighteth againſt the nature of a Sacrament: for how can it be a ſigne, and the thing it ſelfe?</p>
            <p>Secondy, if we be fed with the accidents of Bread and Wine? It ſhould followe, that our bodies, ſhould be accidentall bodies: bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in ſhewe, and not bodies in deede and of ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it were to deny, that Chriſt tooke fleſh of the Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> if the ſubſtance of Bread and Wine doo become his fleſh; or els to ſay, he had a mixte bodie; either of which is blaſphemie. <hi>Matth. 1.23. Rom. 1.3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, it were to make Chriſt to haue a fantaſticall bodie, if his naturall bodie bée in euerie place, after the words of conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, it were to deny Chriſts Aſcenſion and his ſitting at Gods right hand, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as to ſay, the reſurrection is paſt. <hi>Act. 1.9, 10.</hi> and <hi>3.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, it were to make him ſubiect to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption as the Bread and Wine is. <hi>Phil. 3.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:13766:80"/>
20, 21. 1. Timo. 1.17, 18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seauenthly, it were to make Chriſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to ſinne, for the Bread and Wine becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth our ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Eightly, they moſt blaſphemouſlie affirme, by this their opinion, that Chriſt ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into our draught: O monſtrous blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie. <hi>Matth. 15.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ninthly, if it were the very body of Chriſt, that the Apoſtles did eate at the laſt ſupper: then where was the body that muſt ſuffer for our ſakes: a fantaſticall bodie could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme vs. And if they did eate but halfe of the bodie, and left the other halfe to ſuffer: we could not be redeemed by halfe. Herein therefore wee may ſee how fooliſh a doctrine Poperie is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our ſauiour Chriſt (who is verie trueth, and cannot lie) ſaieth; take, eate, this is my bodie: and therefore his verie bodie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Sauiour Chriſt calleth himſelf a doore, a vine, a waie, and is alſo called a rocke, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a theefe, and ſaide to bee the daye
<pb facs="tcp:13766:81"/>
Starre. <hi>Iohn. 10.7.</hi> and <hi>15.1.</hi> &amp; <hi>14.6. 1. Cor. 10.4. Re. 22.16.</hi> Is Chriſt therefore? a way? a vine? a rock? theefe? and a day Sarre? O no: it were moſt fooliſh and wicked, ſo to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and conclude. He is in deed, the onely doore, thorough whome we muſt enter into ſaluation: the onely waie, to eternall life: the onely tree and roote, from whence we muſt drawe all heauenly and comfortable graces: the ſure rocke to builde on to ſaluation: the theefe to come ſodainely vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wicked to deſtruction: and the glorious wiſdome of his father, to inlighten our hearts, to knowe God to ſaluation. And euen ſo, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the bread his bodie, becauſe it is a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his bodie: that is, it ſheweth how his bodie was crucified and put to death; and the wine his bloud, becauſe it is a ſigne how his bloud was ſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dooth the wicked and vnbeleeuing perſon, receiue the benefit of Chriſts death in recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the externall ſigne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No: for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, they haue not faith. <hi>Titus. 1.1, 2. 1. Theſ. 3.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:13766:81"/>Secondly, they haue not the ſpirit of Chriſt: which things ſhould make them worthie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers of the benefits of Chriſts death, to the remiſſion of ſinnes and euerlaſting life. <hi>Rom. 8.7, 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In receiuing the ſacramental ſignes, do they not bring great hurt to themſelues?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes verely: for firſt they are herein guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the body and bloud of Chriſt. <hi>1. Corin. 11.27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, they eate and drinke their owne damnation. <hi>1. Cor. 11.29.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How can they bee guiltie of the bodie and bloud of Chriſt, to their condemnation: vnleſſe they eate the verie fleſh, and drinke the verie bloud of Chriſt. <hi>1. Cor. 11.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be guiltie of the body and bloud of Chriſt, and to eate vnworthelie to condemnation; is to come raſhely without due examining of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: alſo to come like doggs in their vomit and hoggs in their filthie mier, making no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the holy ſupper, and ſacramental ſignes
<pb facs="tcp:13766:82"/>
ſo that this verie contempt, reacheth vnto the author himſelfe namely Ieſus Chriſt, and his death and bloud ſhedding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What dooth the bread broken, and the wine powred foorth ſignifie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The breaking of the bodie, and the ſhedding of the bloud of Chriſt. <hi>1. Corinthians. 10.16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doo you gather thereby?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, what horrible and vile ſinners we are. <hi>Pro. 20.9. 1. Iohn. 1.1.10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, how wee deſerue the horrible, and intollerable tormentes of hell fier e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtinglie. <hi>Romans. 6.23. Epheſians. 2.2, 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the great loue of GOD, in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his ſonne to take vpon him our nature, and to die for vs to our redemption. <hi>Iohn. 3.16. 1. Iohn. 4.9, 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the great loue of Chriſt, and his humilitie, to humble himſelfe vnto the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed death of the Croſſe and tormentes of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:13766:82"/>
hell for our ſaluation. <hi>Phil. 2.5, 6, 7, 8. Ioh. 10.11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What thinke you of the Papiſtes, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer not the holy ſupper, after the inſtitution of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They deale</p>
            <p>Firſt, iniuriouſlie againſt Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, wickedly againſt the people; in that they bereaue them of ſuch notable vſes, in the breaking of the bread and powring foorth of the Wine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How ſhal we come worthelie to receiue the holy ſupper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt by repentance. <hi>Mark. 1.15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, by faith. <hi>Ephe. 3.16, 17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, by loue. <hi>1. Cor. 10.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, by thankeſgiuing. <hi>Luke. 22.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How may a chriſtian aſſure himſelfe that he commeth in true repentance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If hee bee truely touched with his ſinnes,
<pb facs="tcp:13766:83"/>
and inwardly grieued for them; loathing ſinne from the bottome of his heart; With a true confeſſion vnto GOD, and with a full purpoſe to amende and liue, in the feare of GOD; Then he hath truely repented. <hi>Pſalme. 51.17. Ioel. 2.12, 13. Eſay. 1.16.17. Romans. 12.1, 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How may he perſwade himſelf that he hath a liue lie faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If he feele effectuallie in his heart, the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of Chriſts death, to the remiſſion of ſinnes, and his ſaluation: and confeſſeth Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies herein, hee hath a true and liuelie faith. <hi>Romans. 3.24. Galathians 2.20. Colloſ. 1.21, 22, 23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How in true loue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If he hartelie forgiue his neighbours for the offences and iniuries done againſt him: alſo, if he be ready to doo good vnto all, eſpeciallie vnto the houſe of the faithfull: and finally, if hee haue a care to inſtruct and teach his family, and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in the trueth of GOD, and the faith of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:13766:83"/>
Chriſt: then he may perſwade himſelfe he hath true loue. <hi>Rom. 12.20, 21. Eph. 4.1, 2, 3, 4. col. 3.12, 13, 14, 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How in thankſgiuing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If from the heart both in word and workes, he giue all praiſe and glorie to GOD through Chriſt, for the benefites of ſaluation; and not attribute them to his owne wiſedome, power, and riches; neither yet to burie them in the pit of forgetfulneſſe: and finally, doo not turne the grace of God to wantonneſſe. <hi>Pſa. 103.1, 2, 3, 4, 5,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iere. 9.23, 24. Rom. 15. Iud. 4. Rom. 6.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let vs come vnto the third meane, whereby our faith is increaſed and mainteined, by diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and tell me what diſcipline is?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſcipline is the comely order of holy go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment appointed of Chriſt in his Churth, to be exerciſed and vſed of his Miniſters, and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to keep in the good, and to puniſh the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and that to be done in great loue and pittie. <hi>Matth. 16.19. Iohn 20.20. Math. 18.15, 16.
<pb facs="tcp:13766:84"/>
Rom. 12.3, 4, 6, 7, 8. Matth. 18.17. Gal. 6.1, 2, 3,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein ſtandeth it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in exhortations and admonitions. <hi>1. Theſſ. 5.13, 14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, in threatnings and corrections. <hi>2. Tim. 4.2, 3, 4,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in excommunications, &amp; caſting foorth the great offenders (that will not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by theſe procéedings) out of the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the faithfull, and from the parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king at the Lords Table. <hi>1. cor. 5.12. 1. tim. 5.20. Matt. 18.17. Tit. 3.10.11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What are the endes of excommunication?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that a wicked liuer to the great reproach of God and his Goſpell, be not ſuffered among Chriſtians. <hi>1. cor. 5.4, 5. 1. Tim. 1.20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that the good may not be corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted through the continuall familiaritie of the wicked. <hi>1. cor, 5.6. 2. Theſſ. 3.14, 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that hee that hath ſo fallen, may through the ſhame of the world repent, and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:13766:84"/>
ſeeke to be receiued into the Church again, with all meekneſſe. <hi>1. cor. 5.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let vs come now to the laſt meane, that is, Praier, and tell me, who teacheth thee to pray?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Holy ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is Praier?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a reuerent talking with God, with a pure minde, crauing ſuch things as we want, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the holy wil of God. <hi>Phil. 4.6. pſal. 145.18. Iam. 2.3. 1. Iohn. 3.22, 23, 24. Matth. 15.7, 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seing that God knoweth what need we haue before we aske, &amp; that all things ſhall come to paſſe according to his appointed prouidence: wherefore ſhould we pray?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, to obey, and imitate Chriſt our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander. <hi>Mark. 13.33. Pſal. 50.15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to ſtirre vp our ſelues to ſeeke God in truth and humilitie. <hi>1. Theſſ. 5.17, 18. pſal. 145.18, 19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:85"/>Thirdly, that we may thereby vnload our ſelues of manie griefes, and commend al our waies vnto him. <hi>Luk. 18, 13.14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, to exerciſe our faith in medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon the promiſes of God &amp; his works. <hi>Matth. 7.7, 8, 9, 10, 11. Pſal. 143.10, 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, to teſtifie that we confeſſe there is but one (and that a true) God, the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: and that he onely is the Author of all good giftes both earthly &amp; heauenly. <hi>Pſalm. 37.5.</hi> &amp; <hi>55.22. Iam. 1.17. Pſal. 104, 10,</hi> to <hi>16.</hi> &amp; <hi>145.15, 16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What things belong vnto praier?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that we be inwardly touched, and haue a feeling in conſcience of thoſe things that wee pray for: as either for remiſſion of ſinnes, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall graces, or temporall benefits. <hi>Roma. 8.26, 27. Luk. 18.9. Pſal. 6.1, 2, 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, whether by our praiers we haue had experience of Gods goodneſſe, in graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our former requeſts, to confirme our preſent faith. <hi>Pſalm. 116.1, 2, 3, 4,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>2. cor. 1.3, 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that our prayers be in truth and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:13766:85"/>
in ſinceritie of heart, frée from al hipocriſie. <hi>pſa. 4.1.</hi> and <hi>145.18, 19. 2. Tim. 2.19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, that our praiers procéede from faith, with full aſſurance of the helpe of God, &amp; a ſure beliefe to obtaine that which we doo aſke, according to his word &amp; promiſes. <hi>Iam. 1.4, 5. Mark. 11.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, although our praiers be not at the firſt graunted, yet wee muſt not ceaſe to pray. <hi>Luk. 18.1,</hi> to <hi>9. Rom. 12.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vnto whom muſt we make our praiers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Onely vnto God: for, faith onely belongeth vnto him. <hi>Pſal. 50.15. Matt. 6.9. Rom. 10.13, 14. Iere. 17.5, 6, 7, 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Through whom muſt wee make our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Onely through Ieſus Chriſt: who is the onely Mediator and Aduocate, that</p>
            <p>Firſt, maketh interceſſion for his people. <hi>1. Tim. 2.5. 1. Ioh. 2.1, 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, maketh their praiers accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto God his Father, through the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb facs="tcp:13766:86"/>
of himſelfe. <hi>Reu. 8.3, 4, 5. Eph. 5.20. Heb. 13.12, 13 14, 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then it is not lawfull to make our praiers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Angels, Saints, or images: is it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No; it were altogether ſacriledge, &amp; blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſo to doo: for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, it robbeth God of his honour. <hi>Eſa. 42.21, 22. Rom. 2.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it denieth Chriſt to be the onely Mediator and Aduocate. <hi>1. Tim. 2.5. 1. Ioh. 2.1, 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is contrarie to the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God, and rule of Chriſt. <hi>pſalm. 50.15. Matth. 6.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, they are accurſed that do it. <hi>Ier. 17.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, they make thereby, as though Saints and Angels, were more readie to helpe, and more mercifull, than God our lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Father, and Chriſt our ſweete Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By what rule muſt we frame our praiers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:13766:86"/>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Onely by the word of God. <hi>Matthew. 6.9. Luk. 11.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where ſhall we finde the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Lords Praier.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rehearſe the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c. <hi>Matt. 6.9.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Into how manie parts may this praier be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two: as, <list>
                  <item>Firſt, in reſpect of Gods glorie, in the three firſt petitions.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, in reſpect of our ſelues, in the three laſt petitions.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo to this praier belongeth a preface, and a concluſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the preface?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, vnto whom God is a Father, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:13766:87"/>
vnto them, that beléeue in the name of Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Iohn. 1.12, 13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, ſeeing God is become their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (who is moſt mercifull) it dooth incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them to come vnto him; &amp; not to flie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, as a ſeuere Iudge, or a cruell Tyrant. <hi>Micah. 7.18, 19, 20. Pſa. 103.8,</hi> to <hi>13. Heb. 2.10, 11, 12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, who they are that can truely call God their Father: namely, they that haue the Holie ghoſt. <hi>Rom. 8.15. Gal. 4.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, as God is become their Father through his owne Loue: ſo he will loue them vnto the ende. <hi>Rom. 1.7. Ioh. 13.1. Rom. 11.29.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, in that heauen is his throne, it is manifeſt, that he is of power to helpe at all times. <hi>Luk. 1.37. Rom. 8.31, 32, 33.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you by the firſt petition, in the firſt part of this heauenlie praier, <hi>hallowed bee thy name, &amp;c?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that God himſelfe dooth neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe nor decreaſe in reſpect of his glorie, and the greatneſſe of his holineſſe. <hi>Pſalme 48.10.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:13766:87"/>
Malac. 3.6. Iam. 1.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, what his name dooth ſignifie? That is: his word and workes, for in them, is his mercie, power, goodnes and iuſtice made knowne. <hi>1. Tim. 6.1. Pſalm. 102.21. Pro. 18.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, how wee muſt ſanctifie the ſame that is:</p>
            <p>Firſt, in words. <hi>Matth. 5.16. Titu. 2.9, 10. 1. Pet. 3.15, 16. Ro. 11.36. &amp;. 16.27</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, in works. <hi>Matth. 5.16. Titu. 2.9, 10. 1. Pet. 3.15, 16. Ro. 11.36. &amp;. 16.27</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the ſecond petition: <hi>thy kingdome come?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, what this kingdome of Chriſt is, namelie, ſpirituall and externall. <hi>Iohn. 18.36. 2. Pet. 1.3,</hi> to <hi>12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, wherin it conſiſteth in this life, to raigne in the hearts of the faithful; that is, <hi>Luk. 17.20.21. Rom. 14.17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, by his word. <hi>Matth. 3.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, by his holy ſpirit, and both: to increaſe his gifts and grace in vs. <hi>Col. 1.9, 10.13, 14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:88"/>Thirdly, that he wil defend his kingdome againſt the diuel, world, ſinne, eternal death, and all her cruell enemies. <hi>Matth. 28.19. Ephe. 6.18, 19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, that hee would come to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and end the daies of ſinne, and bring vs to the kingdome of his eternall and perfect glorie. <hi>Reuel. 22.25. Phil. 1.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you by the third petition: <hi>thy will be done in earth as it is in heauen?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt what this will of God is <hi>(vz.)</hi> his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed will and not his ſecret; for we ought not raſhely to ſeeke after the ſame. <hi>Deut. 29.29. Rom. 9.20. &amp; 11.33. Colo 1.9, 10. 1. Theſ. 4.1, 2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that our wills (which are moſt corrupt and fooliſh, may bee plucked downe. <hi>Ro. 8.7, 8. 1. Cor. 2.14. Ephe. 4.17.18, 19.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that the holy will of God, may be obeyed of vs in all things (without reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) as the holy Angels in heauen obey with all redines and cheerefulnes. <hi>Pſal. 103.20.21. &amp; Pſal. 143.10.11. Matth. 7.21, 22. Luk. 22.42.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:13766:88"/>Fourthly, if we bee obedient to the will of God? then muſt we ſeeke to learne the ſame, and vſe all the meanes to come vnto the knowledge thereof. <hi>Rom. 12.1. 2. Eph. 5.17. 1. Theſ. 4.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now let vs come to the ſecond parte of the praier, and ſee what we are to learne out of the firſt petition therein? <hi>Giue vs this day our dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bread?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, what daily bread dooth ſignifie, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all things needfull for this life. <hi>Gene. 3.9. 2. Reg. 22.23. Pſal. 104.14, 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, who muſt giue vs the ſame, namely God. <hi>Matth. 6.32.33. Pſal. 127.1.2, 3. and 128.1, 2, 3, 4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that God onely muſt bleſſe all our labors that wee may receaue profit thereof. <hi>Deut. 28. Pro. 3.7, 8, 9, 10. 2. Theſ. 3.8.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, we muſt be contented with that which God giueth vs, and bee thankfull for the ſame though neuer ſo ſmall and ſimple. <hi>Phil. 4.11, 12. 1. Timo. 6.6, 7, 8, 9, 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, in that we muſt praie for the good eſtate and preſeruation of our brethren: and
<pb facs="tcp:13766:89"/>
that, all that is theirs, may proſper, it teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs not to ſpoile them of any thing that is theirs, nor to hurt the ſame. <hi>1. Timo. 4.4. Iohn. 6.11. 1. Theſ. 4.6. Pro. 3.27, 28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How many things learne you in the fift pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition; <hi>forgiue vs our trespaſſes, as wee forgiue them that trespaſſe against vs?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, how all men are ſinners, and none free from ſinne, but all doo breake the lawe of God, both in thought, word, and deed. <hi>Pro. 20.9. and 24.16. 1. Iohn. 1.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, how we haue need therfore to ſeek continuallie for pardon at the hands of God, who onely doth pardon, and that thorough Chriſts death and bloud. <hi>Pſal. 32.5. &amp;. 51.1.</hi> to <hi>7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, this teacheth that man cannot by his merits ſatiſfie Gods wrath inſomuch as he muſt ſeeke forgiuenes. <hi>Eſay. 64.6. Pſalm. 130.3, 4. and 143.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, it ſheweth that we muſt both for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue and forget, if wee will haue our ſinnes both forgiuen and forgotten of God. <hi>Gene. 50.21. Col. 3.13. Mat. 6.14, 15. Mat. 18.35.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:13766:89"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the ſixt and laſt petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? <hi>And lead vs not into temptation, but deliuer vs from euill?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt that although God dooth trie our faith and obedience, by ſatan and his euill ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: yet that he would aſſiſt vs, with his ſpirit of ſtrength and holines, that we neuer be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of them. <hi>Ephe. 6.12,</hi> to <hi>19. 1. Peter. 5.8. Reuel. 12.8, 9, 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it ſheweth how Chriſtians, are at warre with a cruell Lion, a ſubtill ſerpent, and a continuall accuſer: therefore not to ſleepe in ſecuritie. <hi>1. Pet. 5.8. Reuel. 12.8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, how wee muſt ouercome, not in our ſtrength and wiſdome (for they are our enemies, and friends to the diuell) but onelie by the armor of God and ſtrength of Chriſt. <hi>Rom. 8.7. 1. Cor. 1.20. Ephe. 6.10.11, 12, 13, 14. 1. Cor. 5.55,</hi> to <hi>58. Cor. 1.11. 1. Ioh. 5.4.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the diuell can doo nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God giue leaue, and that God wil tempt his children no farther than he wil ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en
<pb facs="tcp:13766:90"/>
and deliuer them. <hi>1. Cor. 10.13. Pſal. 34.18, 19. Iob. 1.12. 1. Sam. 16, 14. Matth. 8.31. Acts. 16.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, what it is to be giuen ouer to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and euill: that is, when GOD giueth man ouer vnto himſelfe, and puniſheth ſinne with ſinne, and hardnes with hardnes of heart. <hi>Acts. 28.25, 26. Matth. 13.14. Ro. 1.24. Rom. 9.17, 18, 1. Reg. 22.21, 22, 23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the concluſion? <hi>For thine is thy kingdome, the power, and the glorie for euer and euer Amen.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, erneſtly to ſeeke after the glory of god <hi>Matth. 6.33. 1. Chro. 29.9, 10. Ro. 11.36.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, we may aſſure our ſelues, that God will graunt vs our godly deſires, for all power and glorie is his, and cannot be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from him. <hi>Pſal. 50.15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that his kingdome ſhall neuer ceaſe, but remaine euerlaſting and glorious. <hi>2. Chro. 29.11, 12, 13. Deu. 4.31. Luk. 1.33.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, that by this worde, <hi>Amen,</hi> wee are taught with what godly mind and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent zeale, we ſhould praie: and with what
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:13766:90"/>
aſſurance to haue our praiers granted. <hi>1. Timo. 1.17. Reuel. 7.12.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What are the ſpirituall benefits, and graces that belong to the Church of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are theſe three chiefely: <list>
                  <item>Firſt, the forgiuenes of ſinnes.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, the reſurrection of the bodie.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, life euerlaſting.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rehearſe the tenth article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The forgiuenes of ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is forgiuenes of ſinnes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A full remoouing of the guiltines, and the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of our ſinnes, by the death and bloud of Chriſt which is our reconciling vnto God. <hi>Rom. 3.24. Ephe. 1.7. Col. 1.12, 13.14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is reconciliation with God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a perfect reſtoring vnto the fauor of God, through the obedience of our only media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
<pb facs="tcp:13766:91"/>
Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>2. Cor. 5.19, 20, 21. Titus. 2.14.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you out of this Article?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that we are all vile ſinners, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neede to ſéeke for pardon. <hi>Matth. 18.24. Iob. 14.4. 1. Iohn. 1.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that the remiſſion of ſinnes comes only by the ſuffrings of Chriſt. <hi>1. Pe. 1.18, 19, 20, 21. Matth. 26.26, 27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that our ſinnes being freelie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen, ſhall bee no more laid to our charges to condemne vs, for Chriſt hath both died for vs, and iuſtified vs. <hi>Rom. 8.32, 33, 34. Iere. 31.34. Heb. 10.16, 17, 18, 19, 20.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the eleuenth article? <hi>the reſurrection of the bodie?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that our mortall bodies, that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed either in the earth, vppon the earth, or in the ſea, ſhall arriſe againe at the laſt day of iudgement, according to the propheſies, and the word of God. <hi>Eſay. 26.19, 20, 21. Dan. 12.2, 3. Iohn. 5.28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:13766:91"/>Secondly, that the reſurrection of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies comes by the benefit we haue of Chriſts reſurrection, and the power of God. <hi>2. Cor. 4.14. Phil. 3.20. 1. Cor. 15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that our bodies ſhall ariſe glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and immortall. <hi>Phil. 3.20, 21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What learne you in the twelft article, <hi>And life euerlasting?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that all the faithfull ſhall haue euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life. <hi>Matth. 25.46. Iohn 14. Iohn 17.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that eternall life, is the free gift of God. <hi>Rom. 8.23. Matth. 25.24.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, by whome that is, onely through faith in Chriſt. <hi>Iohn 6.47. Pet. 1.4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why, is there no mention made in the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of our faith, of the reſurrection of the wicked: with their puniſhment of bodie and ſoule, in hell fier euerlaſtingly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Becauſe this ſumme of faith, reſpecteth one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the benefits of faith, belonging to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:92"/>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why? Shall not the wicked riſe and be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed euerlaſtinglie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes verily: their bodies ſhall ariſe, and bee ioyned to their ſoules, and ſo puniſhed in hel fier for euermore. <hi>Actes 24.15. Iohn. 5.28, 29. 2. Theſ. 1.8. Reuel. 20.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now for good works: tell me, can wee not merit Heauen of our ſelues by our owne good works?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No verely: for ſo to think; were firſt to denie the grace of God. <hi>Ephe. 2.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to ſay that Chriſt died in vaine, and ſo, no ſauiour. <hi>Gal. 2.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, it fighteth againſt faith. <hi>Ga. 2.16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea: but the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward euerie man, according to his workes? Ro. 2.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true: God promiſeth rewards for good deedes (not for the worthines of them but) for the grace wherewith God dooth imbrace the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers, and doth crowne his own gifts in them:
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:13766:92"/>
alſo, to incourage vs to walke obediently, and fruitefullie, in all holines before him and his people. <hi>Matth. 25.33, &amp;c. Rom. 2.6, 7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> biddeth vs to worke out our ſaluation, with feare and trembling? <hi>Phil. 2.22.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame Apoſtle on the other ſide, telleth vs that ſaluation, faith, and good works, are the free gifts of God. <hi>Ephe. 2.10. Titus 3.4, 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why then dooth hee bid vs doo the ſame, if we haue not power to doo it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle, in theſe words, ſeeketh to take away all careles ſecuritie from Chriſtians: and leaſt that Chriſtians ſhoulde take too much vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, he ſetteth downe in the next verſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, that God muſt worke both the wil and deede, and that of his owne good pleaſure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out merit: withal in theſe words he miniſtreth a comfort to his people, in ſhewing them, where they may haue a remedy to helpe their weaknes and inhabilitie. <hi>Phil. 2.13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13766:93"/>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If our ſinnes deſerue eternal death: then our good works deſerue eternall life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is no good concluſion: for, if a man ſhould reaſon thus: This man can kill himſelf, therefore he can giue himſelfe life; may we not thinke him madde. But this obiection <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle anſwereth thus: The wages of ſinne is death, but the gift of GOD, is eternall life, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord: withal, al good gifts proceed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, euil things from vs. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill things are perfectlie euill: &amp; our good works are imperfect and maimed. The reward of the beſt of which is death. <hi>Ro. 6.23. 1. Cor. 13.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What then doo you conclude?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, that eternall life, is the free gift of God by his mercies. <hi>Eph. 2.8. Ti. 3.3, 5. Ro. 6.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that by Chriſts death and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience we purchaſe it. <hi>Ro. 5.6.</hi> to the end.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by faith, as the inſtrument to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the ſame. <hi>Iohn. 3.16. Gal. 2.16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, that we muſt glorifie God, in all good works for our ſaluation. <hi>Matth. 5.16. 1. Pet. 2.12.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:13766:93"/>
            <head>¶A Praier before Catechiſing.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Gratious GOD and deare Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we moſt humbly and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly intreate thee, for thy infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit mercies ſake in thy beloued and onely ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, our free redeemer and ſauiour, that thou wouldeſt bleſſe this thy worke, commanded and deliuered vnto vs thy poore and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſeruants in thy holy word: make the ſame profitable vnto vs, that wee may bee fruitful in al knowledge, ſtrong in faith, and ſanctified in our life and conuerſation, that thereby thy name may by vs, bee glorified, thy children comforted, and our ſoules and bodies in Ieſus Chriſt ſaued, graunt vs theſe things O mercifull father for Chriſts ſake. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A Praier after Catechiſing.</head>
            <p>O Good God and louing father, who art full of mercie vnto the ſinfull ſonnes of men, and moſt gratious vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy elect people (which thou haſt choſen freely in Chriſt Ieſus) we thank thee, in that
<pb facs="tcp:13766:94"/>
thou haſt drawne vs out of ignorance and blindnes, and called vs vnto the vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able light and excellent knowledge of thy ſelf, as a deare and rich father, in Ieſus Chriſt our redeemer: wee beſeech thee increaſe our knowledge more and more, and make our hearts (which are by nature ſtony and hard) ſo ſoft and pliable both to heare, receiue, &amp; obey thy waies in all reuerence and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vnto our liues ende, that we may praiſe thy euerlaſting mercies in Ieſus Chriſt. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A Praier before meales.</head>
            <p>THE Lorde bee thanked, and giue vs grace to be thankefull, the Lord bee mercifull vnto vs, and forgiue vs our ſinnes, the Lord ſanctifie theſe his good cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures for our vſes, and ſanctifie vs vnto his holy Maieſtie through a liuely and pure faith in Ieſus Chriſt our onely ſauiour. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A thankeſgiuing after meales.</head>
            <p>TO thee O good God who hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs by thy wiſdome and power, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed vs when we were loſt by thy rich mercie and ſanctified vs when wee were
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13766:94"/>
poluted and defiled in ſinne by thy free ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, and haſt preſently fed vs by thy plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vnſpeakeable goodnes; bee all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, glorie and power in Ieſus Chriſt. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Faultes eſcaped in <hi>the Printing.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Fol. 9. a line 12. <hi>where</hi> read <hi>were.</hi> Fol. 11. a. line 9. <hi>not onely Angels,</hi> read <hi>not Angels.</hi> Fol. 47. b. line 19. <hi>ought to tie,</hi> read <hi>ought not to tie.</hi> Fol. 59. a. line 20. <hi>brought,</hi> read <hi>bought.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
